<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>out.of.desk</title>
    <description>My Online, Filtered Notepad</description>
    <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://outofdesk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 17:40:29 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 17:40:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A chat with the different selfs</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We all have various sides of our *self*, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about how the pandemic has affected me, I can’t think of one absolute way it has. The experience hasn’t been binary, one that can be categorized into good or bad. We all have various sides of our &lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to think about what those are for me, bring them to light, and get them to talk. Most of them have adapted quite well to the changes necessitated by the constraints of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-different-selfs&quot;&gt;The different selfs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we spend a better part of our lives doing our day job, it naturally defines us in a significant way, if not completely. I work as a software engineer, and it’s one of my important identities, it’s also the one that’s most visible or known to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the integral parts of my job, an activity that is also close to my heart, is to always keep learning. That’s another thing I identify myself with - as someone eager to learn and open to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental, and in some ways more important, part of my identity is one that’s obsessed with practising a healthy lifestyle. I say important because I believe it nourishes the other selfs, and fundamental because it’s less fluid in nature than the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other important dimension is the part of me that cares deeply about animals. I say &lt;em&gt;cares&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt;, because that’s an important distinction, and even though I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; some animals, I want to be mindful about the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one other aspect of me has stood the test of time. I don’t have much control over it, and I’ve had a love-hate relationship with it, more hate than love - my introverted nature. More hate than love because I’ve only recently started to accept, and nurture it, rather than treating it like a problem that needed fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next one is a close kin of the self that wants to lead a healthy life, but is more opinionated on how to go about it. It believes in spending time in nature, and doing physically challenging things to keep the body and the mind in good shape. The curious and learning part of me constantly feeds this self, with new ideas, challenges to tackle and goals to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one I can think of is the most volatile of them all, and has only come to consciousness very recently. It swims up to the surface and goes back to hiding depending on the things that’s happening around me - the one that thinks of itself as an immigrant in a foreign country, a guest in someone else’s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I try to prod each one of them to express their thoughts about how they feel being sheltered in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-a-software-engineer&quot;&gt;As a software engineer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s fairly easy to work remotely and still be productive. While I miss the walks and talks around the office with my peers to get coffee during the day, I’ve made up for it by experimenting with different kinds of plant-based milk coffees at home. After several weeks of trial-and-error, it’s getting close to my liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate that wifi at home is not as good and causes, part frustrating, part funny, technical issues while talking to my colleagues on video calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also miss the desk setup and multiple monitors I used to have in the office, but for now, I’m managing with an REI camp chair, a laptop and a monitor. It’s easy to get lost in work and forget how or where I’m sitting at home. Stiffness from bad body postures used to be a problem in the first weeks, but I’ve gotten more mindful about that over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/engineer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to wait for meeting rooms to free up to chat with people - they’re just a few clicks and a video call away. I think it’s more productive and collaborative than an open-office setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to rush to catch the train and sit through a long commute to get to work in the morning, and that I can start working early in the day when my mind is at its best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first few weeks, I worked more than usual, and so did my peers. But I’ve gotten better at drawing boundaries between work and personal life, even without a physical one separating the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing I don’t miss is the incessant chatter in the office, where unnecessary small talk is confused with collaboration and coding is confused with mindless typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the things I don’t miss from going to work and the things I love about working from home, I’d do more remote work going forward for sure, and hope companies embrace it more too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-avid-reader&quot;&gt;As an avid reader,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that the two or more hours I used to spend riding in train to go to work, I now spend riding in train of thoughts, one that takes me to farther and better places. Reading not only helps me unplug from the stress and concerns of work, but the comfort and peace of doing it from home improves my mood. The absence of distractions of a typical workday has helped me do more of a fewer things rather than juggle a little bit of everything. Long stretches of undistracted time allows me to focus on reading books, long-form articles and write more, rather than filling the tiny slices of time over the day with news and junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absence or lack of something usually makes you realize its importance, but it’s interesting in a way that having more, and not less, time in hand has made me realize how much of it was being taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/reading.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also starting to see the benefits of consistency and discipline, of cultivating enough patience to do something everyday despite the initial aversion and resistance, and how it can make a big difference relatively quickly. Though I have been trying to get into the habit of writing for over a year, I’ve only been this consistent and serious about it since I started working from home. The world had to hit brakes on its operations and get rid of distractions for me to start writing. It’s like the Universe really wanted to teach me good habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-outdoor-enthusiast&quot;&gt;As an outdoor enthusiast,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really worried about not being able to travel. I had a few races that I had signed up for and a few trips I had planned for this year. But sitting at home, not having hiked or biked in a couple of months now has taught me that I don’t need to go to new places to freshen up my mind, or to enjoy outdoors every time I head out. That I can just step out of the door and start running until I get tired and run back. That it can be that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started running a couple of years ago for the fun of it, and maybe a little to lose weight too, but over time, I started getting obsessed over quantifying the benefits of every activity - the calories burnt, pounds lost, and speed etc,. I’m now back to those simple days. Not every run now goes in Strava, not every race has to end up in PRs, not every walk now is a hike and not every bike ride is captured in photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/outdoor.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solace I used to find in the outdoors, I’ve found it in reading and writing too. Although there is something magical about being out in nature, I realize that one of the reasons it felt so good was the time it gave me to pause, and reflect on things. Turns out books do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-introvert&quot;&gt;As an introvert,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m in love with the silence. It not only helps me think clearly, and be more productive at work, it also puts me in a much better mood overall. Even after working long hours, I find that I have the time and energy to go on walks with my wife, cook, go for a run, read, write and talk to friends and family on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/introvert.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the idea of minimizing sounds that fall in my ears, the idea of letting them in willingly rather than being bombarded with unnecessary and unsolicited noises all day long and being forcefully made a passive member in every conversation around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-immigrant&quot;&gt;As an immigrant&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from India, I see the contrast in how people from the two countries are reacting to the pandemic, both common people and those in power. Being from the majority group in India, and a part of one of the minority groups(immigrants) here in the US, it gives some perspectives on how stereotypes and misinformation against minorities are used for political and capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’m concerned about the well-being of older members of my family back home and wish I were there, a part of me feels relieved that I’m not with them to inadvertently infect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/immigrant.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see through the lies and the facade of developed societies and feel hopeful and optimistic, to see the potential of the developing nations and their simple, yet effective ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the things that have worked for countries and things that haven’t, I realize that more technology is not necessarily the right solution to all problems. Common sense and empirical evidence are perfectly fine at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-animal-rights-believer&quot;&gt;As an animal rights believer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that non-humans have started to come out of hiding and are doing so without the fear of us harming, or killing them, that at least for a little while they regain their rights over the resources of this planet, and not everything they consume are left-overs from humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/animals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m terribly sad and shocked by the fate of hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of animals in factory farms that were killed because humans couldn’t afford to raise and kill them to eat. I can’t decide which is worse, simply killing them, or killing to eat them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that meat substitutes are seeing tremendous growth and hope that the trend continues long after our lives get back to &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt;. Although it’s a result of shortage of meat in markets right now, I hope that reduced meat and dairy consumption becomes the new normal, and people see it for what it actually is, and the problems it puts us into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slow-life-vs-fast-life&quot;&gt;Slow life vs fast life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say the world has slowed down during the pandemic, but what does it mean to be slow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we truly slowed now, or were we unnecessarily fast before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was the rush anyway, and where were we all headed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were we navigating towards a perceived sense of growth and success, or were we merely racing towards a mountain of problems created by our own greed and speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the rush was in fact necessary, why does slow feel better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the age of mind and innovation, than of body and physical labor, then why were cruising in autopilot, without stopping to think about the destination?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that the fast life we chose in pursuit of something good only made us more miserable and unhealthy, and this life of nothingness is making us happier, and healthier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that we’re regaining the connections we had lost, by distancing ourselves? That we had to be physically social-distanced to close the mental and emotional gap between each other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas and learnings from a lot of reading and collaboration between multiple dimensions of my self has gone into producing this. Of all the news and information that’s out there about the pandemic, a majority of them either portray humans as the victims, not the villains, or blame a specific section of people for all the problems. With such lopsided, and biased opinions floating around, this one below stands out with a different perspective on things and makes for a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I’ve come to shut down the machine whose emergency brake you couldn’t find
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lundi.am/What-the-virus-said&quot;&gt;What the virus said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reflection/self/pandemic/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reflection/self/pandemic/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflection</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>pandemic</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fine Walls</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been more than a month since we started working from home and about a month since our county put the shelter-in-place in effect. We’ve limited our outdoor trips just to walks every evening, and grocery shopping once a week. The rules and recommendations around the importance and usefulness of everybody wearing a mask are shifting by the day - from being useless to being essential. That, mixed with the concern of shortage of masks for healthcare workers has spiked online content teaching people how to make DIY masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my wife and I went grocery shopping today, the best we could do was use scarves as masks. I realized, there’s something about hiding your face in public that makes you feel uncomfortable. Not that it’s a bad idea in these times, but it still feels weird nonetheless, especially the first few times. Maybe it’s a cultural thing or availability bias that has rooted this idea in our minds that bad guys do that - people looting a bank cover their faces, terrorists cover their faces. Sure, doctors and nurses wear masks too, but the human brain doesn’t recollect such images when we think about people hiding behind masks. And since face is such a crucial part of our identity, hiding it equates to hiding one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wore the scarf around my face, I also thought about how anti-social it makes us seem. Even in a country like the US, where individualism and personal freedom lie at the core of the culture, where loneliness is an epidemic and where people are terrified to make accidental eye contact with strangers, wearing a mask seems especially anti-social in some way. It puts a physical boundary between two identities and hence validates the invisible distance between us that already currently exists. With a mask, you now don’t need to fear awkward eye contact with strangers or running into someone you know but don’t want to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t be surprised if a majority of people here will continue to wear masks after this, not for the fear of infection, but for the liberty to be themselves in public. It’s ironic then that wearing a mask will give us the liberty to throw away the mask of social identity. It looks like a way to mute one of the primary ways we communicate with each other, a way to bring anonymity offered by the Internet out into the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar boundary was drawn not too long ago, to mute one of our other primary channels of communication. When I started my first job out of school a few years ago in India, every employee had their cubicle to work. It indicated a piece of space in a huge commercial floor plan which you could call your private little corner. When I got back into the workforce two years later, out of graduate school, those boundaries were gone, or so I thought. While the idea of open office floor plans was to encourage people to be more social, I learned about the existence of a relatively new, unacknowledged, or rather differently advertised boundary, which wasn’t as far as the walls of cubicles but much closer to us - the headphones. Just like the walls of our homes,which signal the line separating our family from the outside world, headphones draw a boundary between the sounds and voices we &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to let in and everything else. With the introduction of designer and handy AirPods, that boundary has become more commonplace and prevalent and has jumped out of the confinement of the walls of office space. So I can’t help but think and feel bad about the fact that there’s tons of money to be made in the future from the fear we’re now living in and that those solutions will make us, incrementally and permanently, more distant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/society/culture/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/society/culture/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>society</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Summary: Behind the Smiles by Reveal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In March 2014 when I got an offer from Amazon for a summer internship, I couldn’t have been happier. I was happy for two reasons, one, because I needed a break from interviewing and two because it was Amazon. I didn’t know which team I was going to be working with at the time and only a few weeks before my internship, I learned that I was matched with Labor Optimization Team in Amazon Fulfillment Technologies(AFT) org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job as an intern in the team was to help build systems to make sense of the data and the models designed to analyze it by the data scientist we had. There was a lot of data about the workers working in the Fulfillment Centers, like their smoking habits, for example, and one of the goals of the team was to be able to learn and predict characteristics of people that made them stick to the job and bring down the attrition rate. I had heard how people moved in and out of these jobs and how it was hard to find workers who stayed. I didn’t think much about why that was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make us better at our jobs and help us understand the whole process, we were even flown to a Fulfillment Center during the internship. I forgot which one it was, but it had Kiva robots to move the big racks around. It was amazing to see how robots were serving humans here, doing the laborious task of carrying heavy boxes for long distances in these gigantic warehouses. Never thought about what happened after the robots brought those boxes to humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following is a summary of the article reported by Reveal on the conditions of workers at Amazon Fulfillment Centers and the cost of the ever-increasing speed of home delivery. Read on for my highlights and key takeaways from the article. You can find the original article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.revealnews.org/article/behind-the-smiles&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Injury rates are extremely high in Amazon Fulfillment Centers(warehouses). Serious injuries, which require time off from work, are double the industry average in warehouses. In some fulfillment centers and in certain times of the year, it is up to four to even six times the industry average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracking system for each of the task – pick, stow, pack and so on are immensely efficient and fierce. Scanners have to scan an item about every 11 seconds. Pickers are required to pick about 385 small or 350 medium boxes every hour. They get written up and eventually terminated for even 98.5% efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warehouses with robots are worse for workers since the expectations from them go higher when the robots get faster and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job advertisements don’t mention any skills or experience required, but the training is insufficient and expectations sky-high, when they actually start working. Holidays and peak seasons are the worst when a huge number of temporary, seasonal workers are hired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workers are too afraid of termination and retaliation to even talk about their issues or take restroom breaks. All their breaks are rigorously tracked and marked “time-off task” and their pleas fall into deaf ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some report that they had to pee in bottles, or take packages to restrooms with them to avoid missing the quota. Some have suffered urinary tract infections from holding it in for long times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of the death of a worker in Indiana operating a forklift in the warehouse was covered up and people investigating pushed back by the higher officials all the way up to the Mayor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t help but draw parallels between the almost robotic efficiency expected from humans in these warehouses to slaughterhouses in factory farms. The ever-increasing demand for stuff(packages and meat) has pushed industries to meet it at the expense of human, animal and planet health. It’s a classic case of human greed and indifference taking a toll on anyone and anything that’s poor, vulnerable and helpless. I won’t be surprised if companies like Amazon go as far to use its power and influence to get something like the ag-gag laws passed to make it illegal to record in any form the conditions of workers in its Fulfillment Centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some similarities between the two industries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both are driven by the need for speed and increased demand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers in both the industries suffer a lot more serious injuries than the industry average in jobs requiring physical labor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers in both the industries have reported not being sent to a doctor by their on-site medical staff even after multiple reports of pain and injuries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers sometimes are told not to use unplanned restroom breaks, and other times they don’t do it out of fear of missing their quota. Some have reported using adult diapers, or peeing in a bottle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Products from the industries are eventually shipped in boxes and wrappers with smiles on them, which is utter disinformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;highlights&quot;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The clock was always ticking on Amazon’s promised delivery time. Dixon had to scan a new item every 11 seconds to hit her quota, she said, and Amazon always knew when she didn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…in the last holiday season, they hit a coveted target: They got a million packages out the door in 24 hours. Amazon handed out T-shirts celebrating their induction into the “Million Unit Club.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“An Amazon-approved doctor said she had bulging discs and diagnosed her with a back sprain, joint inflammation and chronic pain, determining that her injuries were 100% due to her job.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the rate of serious injuries for those facilities was more than double the national average for the warehousing industry: 9.6 serious injuries per 100 full-time workers in 2018, compared with an industry average that year of 4.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson said Amazon’s injury rates are high because it’s aggressive about recording worker injuries and cautious about allowing injured workers to return to work before they’re ready.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When a gas leak inundated the Eastvale warehouse where Dixon used to work, managers wouldn’t slow down, several workers said, even though they were dizzy and vomiting. They were told that they’d have to use personal time off if they wanted to leave.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the holiday season, “…warehouses are crammed with seasonal workers unaccustomed to the grind. The company’s 2018 logs show weekly injury counts spiked at two distinct moments when Amazon offers special deals: Cyber Monday and Prime Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson, the Amazon spokesperson, said total injuries do go up during those peak times, but that’s only because the company brings on more workers then.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But injury records and interviews with three of the former Amazon safety managers suggest the introduction of the robots led to even more injuries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““Before robots, it was still tough, but it was manageable,” he said. Afterward, “we were in a fight that we just can’t win.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The U.S. Department of Labor under the Obama administration proposed posting them online, but under President Donald Trump, the agency has reversed course and also has fought public records requests. And Amazon has resisted making its own safety records public.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He said higher-ups instructed him to come up with justifications for not recording injuries that should have been counted by law.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…Terry showed up for work and was sent to do maintenance on a forklift. He walked under the machine’s forks and metal platform to work on it with a wrench. Suddenly, the 1,200-pound piece of equipment dropped down and crushed him.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Stallone repeatedly pressed Amazon to provide records showing Terry had been trained on that piece of equipment. In the end, he found that Amazon failed to provide adequate training, exposing Terry to a fatal hazard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During the call, Alexander told the Amazon officials what she’d need from them in order to shift the blame from the company to “employee misconduct,” according to the recording.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Holcomb told him how much it would mean to Indiana if the state won the Amazon headquarters deal. Then, Stallone said, the commissioner told him to back off on the Amazon case – or resign.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A year after Terry’s death, Indiana officials quietly signed an agreement with Amazon to delete all the safety citations and fines. The agreement said Amazon had met the requirements of an “unpreventable employee misconduct defense.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““If there was any misconduct there, it’s putting a person that has little to no experience and working on this piece of equipment,” said the other former safety manager, who has worked at multiple facilities. “Whoever allowed that to happen – that’s the misconduct.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…had been smelling gas since the start of her shift. Some workers had been moved to another part of the building, and others were sent briefly to a break room, but the warehouse had not been evacuated, according to accounts by Van Vorce and four others at work that night.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson told Reveal that Amazon shut down the site for about an hour and a half while a maintenance team repaired the leak. But Van Vorce tells the dispatcher that management wouldn’t stop operations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““They’re trying to tell us we have to use our personal time if we want to leave,” she says in the 911 recording.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…picker at a fulfillment center in Phoenix until last year, said he and other workers would bring customers’ orders into the bathroom with them to scan midway through. “It sounds disgusting,” he acknowledged.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““You have to hold your pee or not make your rate. Which one you want to do?” Shrum said. “I had to make my rate.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.revealnews.org/article/behind-the-smiles&quot;&gt;Reveal – Behind the Smiles: Amazon’s internal injury records expose the true toll of its relentless drive for speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2016/05/25/479509221/we-dont-know-how-many-workers-are-injured-at-slaughterhouses-heres-why&quot;&gt;NPR – We Don’t Know How Many Workers Are Injured At Slaughterhouses. Here’s Why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2018/jul/05/amputations-serious-injuries-us-meat-industry-plant&quot;&gt;The Guardian – Two amputations a week: the cost of working in a US meat plant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/capitalism/technology/2019/11/27/summary-behind-the-smiles.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/capitalism/technology/2019/11/27/summary-behind-the-smiles.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>capitalism</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Entrepreneurship and Dogs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2013, I was working in a startup with a team of about 10 engineers when one day we were all called for a team meeting. The founders were in the meeting so we knew it was something important. We were informed that the company was shutting down due to lack of funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had received admit a few days ago from one of the graduate schools I had applied to in the US and so I had a plan and two to three months of vacation ahead. One of the senior engineers in the team decided to work on his venture. Other people started looking for jobs, some founded their own companies too. He asked me if I would be willing to work with him to help build a Proof of Concept(POC). I had nothing to lose here. If it went well, I could always stay and potentially become a co-founder(yes, I passed that opportunity to go to graduate school!) or I could fly to the US in a few months and begin another new phase. It was a win-win for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he had savings to afford not having a job for up to a year and he knew a couple of people who could potentially invest in his idea. After we built the POC, we drove around to places on his motorbike, with our laptops and a “tea-and-biscuits” pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day after we parked the bike, he looked at a street dog sleeping on the road and told me something in Hindi(translated to English here): “We should have been born as those fucking street dogs. Didn’t have to worry so much about jobs or founding a company! We could just sleep all day.” That to me was hilarious. Something about his tone, his facial expression, the casual delivery and the humor about his struggle made it really funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think back on it and that episode seems profound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells something about human desire and imagination&lt;/em&gt; - How we always seek meaning in our lives, how we have this power to create something new, and even the audacity to imagine what a dog’s life must be like!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells about the attitude one can have even in difficult situations in life&lt;/em&gt; - The fact that he said that signals his frustration and anxiety, but also his attitude to make something funny out of it, rather than brooding over the situation and do nothing&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells something about the stories, sometimes false narratives we tell ourselves to get through life, our ability to see the “grass as always greener on the other side”&lt;/em&gt; - How we think others’ lives are easy, and that it would be so much better if we could trade their lives with ours. We only look at tiny slices of someone’s life and simplify them to make ourselves feel better.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;drive&lt;/strong&gt; that almost robs us of free will and calls the shots in our lives&lt;/em&gt; - His wife was pregnant at the time and was staying with her parents, so he had a couple of months to devote himself to something. He had enough money to take a vacation, but he chose (or was forced by his drive) to struggle, and to push himself to embark on a new and unknown journey.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He pivoted from the original idea that we had worked on but his company received a couple of rounds of funding and seems to be doing well now. So I guess he has moved on to define some new struggles and goals for himself to chase, as we always do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/struggle/2019/11/26/entrepreneurship-and-dogs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/struggle/2019/11/26/entrepreneurship-and-dogs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>struggle</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Caring About Animals</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We tried to explain that we were interested in the prevention of suffering and misery; that we were opposed to arbitrary discrimination; that we thought it wrong to inflict needless suffering on another being, even if that being were not a member of our own species; and that we believed animals were ruthlessly and cruelly exploited by humans, and we wanted this changed. Otherwise, we said, we were not especially “interested in” animals.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Peter Singer, in Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a million things to care about in this world if we cared to care about – things that we know are systematically unfair, unjust or outright wrong. But if we cared about all of them to a point where we wanted to fix them or be a part of the solution, we’d go crazy. One way to maintain sanity is to accept that there are going to be things that are and will be out of our control and to learn to let go of some. That leaves us with time and energy to think about what we value the most and work towards fixing them, in any way and capacity we can. Elon Musk might be a rare exception, or at least the most popular of them out there, who can not only think about but make a huge impact on solving a lot of the pressing issues in the world today. But to make my point, even he is not consciously and primarily working towards fixing let’s say the gun violence in America or the use of social media for disrupting elections and attempts to shake the institution of democracy. Most often, people care about a lot of things, but in varying degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I care a lot about my autonomy and growth, health and fitness, to an extent where I spend a considerable amount of my time and energy learning about them, experimenting with them and optimizing them. I also care about the environment and animal welfare but to a point where I don’t proactively do a whole lot to cause any actual change, but I keep myself constantly educating about them and do the best I can without going above and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been brought up a vegetarian my entire life because of religious beliefs, I neither questioned nor observed any inconsistencies in the foods we consumed and the stories we told ourselves about them. I always cared about animals and after reading about and watching the horrors of the dairy industry, I finally decided to give up dairy and egg and go vegan. It wasn’t easy in the beginning, but it happened at once when the evidence of the ill-effects of dairy, on my health and animals, was too clear and overwhelming to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve often felt out of place in vegan and animal welfare circles where people name the rescued animals, celebrate their birthdays, make them desserts and kiss them on their mouths. In that sense, I’m not an animal lover. I deeply care about animals, a bit more than I care about humans I’d say, and I can’t stand abuse or violence against them. I have cried just reading accounts of the treatment of animals for meat and fashion. I remember one time in fifth grade, right in front of my home, a few stray dogs had brutally injured a baby pig. The dogs neither killed nor ate its flesh. They injured it enough that it couldn’t move. If you’ve ever heard the noise of a pig squealing, you know it’s not a pleasant one. I cried my heart out and skipped school that day because I couldn’t step out of the door. It was a slow, painful death, for the pig and some tiny part of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also very sensitive to the blood of animals. I can’t see it. I’d probably faint if I saw an injured animal up close, bleeding. So, while I am hopelessly emotional about animals, I’m not mentally tough enough to help one, bloodily injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while reading &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;, a classic by Peter Singer, I realized that you don’t have to love animals to care about them and to believe in their moral rights and ethical treatment. You don’t have to have loved or even met a person in your life who has been a victim of some kind of discrimination, to ideologically believe that discrimination in any form - racial, sexual, intellectual - is immoral and wrong. So why expect that a person should love animals to believe in their welfare, autonomy, and rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d probably never own a pet, again. But that shouldn’t necessarily stop me from thinking or talking about animal welfare. It’s not an inconsistency, it’s irrelevant. Similarly, owning a pet doesn’t tell much about the extent to which a person cares about animals in general. The fundamental shift in thinking comes from a belief that non-human animals are not that different from us, and acknowledge, what’s now proved beyond doubt, that they experience pain and suffering very much like us. Once that’s established, other arguments start to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we get into a debate about this with others, it’s not so much about those animals as much as it’s about the moral values, prejudices, and biases we hold so dear. That’s why it reaches the level of intensity it does and gets the kind of emotional, sometimes irrational responses that it gets. It’s seeing the belief system collapse, or being shown the inconsistency and hypocrisy in what we think and do that gets to us. People often think that vegans and animal welfare activists ride on moral high ground. One argument to that is that people who sense that arrogance or superiority in others, might have a deep, latent insecurity about their own beliefs on a certain level. Another is that even if people who care about animals aren’t on higher ground, they are not on the lower ground either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you get into a discussion about this with someone with a different opinion, thinking of the following things might help to have a productive and sane debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think non-human animals are inferior to humans? If they do, on what grounds?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think animals experience pain and suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they believe torture and killing of some animals are different than others?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they know about the practices or treatment of animals being killed for meat and fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think that their preferences and likes matter more than the lives of animals?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From answers to these, you’ll know where they stand, and how likely they are to listen and understand your point of view. And if you can’t do a good job communicating your arguments, just ask them to read &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;. No matter what their argument is, I’m sure Peter Singer will have a better, more convincing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Animal-Liberation-Definitive-Classic-Movement/dp/0061711306&quot;&gt;Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/a&gt; (I’m currently reading this myself)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics/568/&quot;&gt;The Rights of Animals: A Very Short Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>animals</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time to Read</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
But I soon came to feel that teaching these sensitive young souls Latin and mathematics was cheating them of something far more essential — what they needed wasn’t dry information but hope, the kind that comes from being transported into a dream-world of possibility.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Helen Fagin, in The Velocity of Being: Letters to a Young Reader&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a chilly weekend morning. I’m standing by the side of a huge lake along with tens of other people, all rubbing their hands together to keep themselves warm. The water looks freezing and turbulent as if to throw us back on land if we were to venture out to take a dip. We’re all waiting for the organizers to blow a whistle to start the first leg of the triathlon. The shot’s fired and everybody starts jumping into the lake like a herd of lemmings out to commit suicide(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalplanet.com/wild-animals/do-lemmings-commit-suicide/&quot;&gt;it’s a myth, they apparently don’t actually do it&lt;/a&gt;). A punch here, a kick there and the unforgiving water. Bruised and exhausted, I somehow make it to the other end to see my bike ready to go. I take off my swim clothes, put on my biking outfit and I’m ready to go. The first half of the biking route is all uphill, and that’s where I plan to get ahead of everybody. My quads looking like wooden logs can hardly be contained in the biking shorts. I pedal as fast as I can on the uphill to pass people who beat me in water. At the top, I bring my back closer to the bike and take off in an aerodynamic position. Even with the sunglasses, tears from my eyes due to the headwinds fly backward as if they’re going to pierce through the rider behind. At the finish line, I apply the brakes, jump off the bike and let it ride further a few yards and crash on its own, like a bird with its neck chopped off. I change to running shorts and slowly ramp my speed in the last and final activity, the one that seems most familiar to me - running. Halfway through the race, somebody tells me that I have a shot at winning and by a huge margin. Tears out again but of happiness and joy this time. The last couple hundred feet I almost sprint as though my legs are green. I win the event and I see my parents at the finish line smiling. I sense a feeling of pride in their eyes, which makes me want to cry more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such vivid is the recollection of the triathlon that never happened. That’s right. While reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.richroll.com/finding-ultra/&quot;&gt;Finding Ultra&lt;/a&gt;, as I read the account of his feats in Hawaii, I pause for a few minutes and get lost in this imaginary race and I’m winning. I probably will never actually win a triathlon. But that imaginary race was still a very powerful motivator. Three years later, that and many such thoughts have fueled real and positive changes in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always felt at peace reading a book in a quiet place. I feel energized and excited to get to places where reading takes me. That feeling of getting inundated with ideas, freeing yourself from the constraints and conditioning of the real-world and letting your mind escape into a world of infinite potential and possibilities, asking yourself big questions and looking for answers within, is hugely inspiring and empowering. In that space and time, you’re neither in auto-pilot nor in the passenger seat. You’re the one in complete control. Making wrong moves there or taking a wrong turn doesn’t come with the judgments and repercussions of the real world. Instead, it comes with a deeper understanding of the consequences and rewards of your choices and helps you navigate the real world better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s much harder these days to get that lone space and time, harder than it needs to be. The eight or so hours that you spend at work is flooded with frequent and sometimes unnecessary meetings, direct or indirect conversations and breaks. You go home, spend some time with your partner, and eke out some time to read, write and workout. Not only do you have to carve time out for deep work, but you also have to make an extra effort to quell the mental chatter caused by entropy throughout the day. With the open floor plans in offices now, the passive conversations that you become part of just by being there feels like passive smoking to me. You end up bearing the brunt of something that you didn’t consciously choose to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it always is an ongoing battle to make time for things, the process of fighting for it also tells you something about what you value most, the things you consider are worth your time and that clarity eventually forces you to let go of the clutter - physical and mental, literal and metaphorical. So in a way, the fight for time is actually a fight for values, self-awareness, growth, a fight to shape and refine yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2018/12/18/a-velocity-of-being-helen-fagin/&quot;&gt;A 100-Year-Old Holocaust Survivor on How Books Save Lives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;Life is Short&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading</category>
        
        <category>time</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Ultra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long bike ride in July up in Colorado, I took it easy for a while and didn’t have any immediate goals to pursue. Had a couple of trips planned with my wife and some day hikes
during the weekends, but that’s about it. I was turning 30 in October and a random goal popped in my mind - to run at least 30 miles. The shortest official distance
that meets the criterion is 50k, which is about 32 miles. The longest I had run so far was a 35k the year before, which is about 22.5 miles. So it looked like an ambitious, formidable, yet doable challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past the Labor Day weekend, so I had already lost the first week of September and since I wanted to do the race in the same month as my birthday, I had about 6-7 weeks to train. It seemed like a short time to go from 0 miles of running the whole year to 50k in a stretch, so I had to start as soon as possible. I started the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the training looked like in numbers. If you’re into long-distance running, you can tell that it looks like casual, weekday runs, nothing like training for an ultra at all. It’s true. Having made plans for the weekends ahead with my family and friends, weekdays were all I could get. Tried to squeeze at least two runs per week, mostly somewhere between 5-8 miles during lunch. The longest run was about 10.5 mi and that was three weeks before the race. Sometimes due to lack of time, and sometimes because of my own laziness, I
didn’t go longer than that. And those long runs were on flat roads, so I wasn’t getting any elevation training either. The race had about 5k ft of gain and descent. The thought of that in addition to pounding the legs for that long, scared me. The last two weeks I ventured out to hilly blocks in the city around my workplace and did some circuit runs to get my body(legs and glutes especially) used to uphills and downhills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---september&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - September&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-september.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar September&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---october&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - October&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-october.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar - October&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-log&quot;&gt;Run Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Log&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-distance&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-time&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-distance&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-time&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/the-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Race&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-reflections&quot;&gt;Notes and Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The race had a no-cup policy, so I carried a Nathan water bottle with me in hand. I think that works better for me than carrying a hydration pack, which rubs my back and gets the shirt all wet&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chafing is the worst. Even now, days after the race, my nipples hurt just thinking about it. I think right around mile 13, I took off my shirt and carried it pretty much from there up to a few yards before the finish line. I should take better care of it next time! Vaseline helps I think but I should look into some strap that hugs it tight and doesn’t cause friction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next time I sign up for something like this, I should do longer runs and on trails. That takes care of the boredom of long runs and also makes for a better training&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t get bored in trail runs. I had prepared a playlist of workout music and motivating podcasts to keep me going, especially in the end. But one, I didn’t need it and two, it ruins the fun of the race. When I slowed down in the last third of the race, I enjoyed the company of runners who were with me. Chatting with them, running with them helped me even speed up a little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GU is delicious and works well, I think. It’s really easy to eat on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gear&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newbalance.com/pd/Minimus-Trail-10/190325795818.html?ecid=ps_Google_pla_190325795818_1699205516&amp;amp;crtp=paidsearch&amp;amp;ncr=true&amp;amp;&amp;amp;CATARGETID=172000630002405320&amp;amp;CADevice=c&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAjwxt_tBRAXEiwAENY8hU7bNqAaUvQr4sk556T2MGHF4m5J3F30Jy7qvvDe9b_MznLsEbPS1BoCsSIQAvD_BwE&amp;amp;gclsrc=aw.ds#color=Black_with_Silver&amp;amp;size=8&amp;amp;width=2E&quot;&gt;New Balance Minimus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nathansports.com/collections/hydration/products/speedmax-plus-flask&quot;&gt;Nathan Handheld Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>running</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
