<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>out.of.desk</title>
    <description>My Online Notepad</description>
    <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://outofdesk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 22:50:16 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 22:50:16 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Grand Canyon R2R2R - Notes and Reflections</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At around 5.30 pm on a Friday, my friend and I were riding in a shuttle bus that carried us from the visitor center to South Kaibab trailhead in Grand Canyon National Park. We had just arrived in the area, set up our tents at Mather Campground, and drove to the visitor center. I could feel butterflies in my gut because of the excitement, fear, and nervousness I was going through, all at the same time, for what we were about to embark on. It’s a familiar feeling, an old friend. It’s the same feeling I get before a public presentation or some kind of a test. It’s also something I feel before every adventure. It indicates that whatever I’m about to do is important enough to make me want to do it regardless of the outcome. There’s a certain element of fear involved too, of failure, because of the high stakes that I attach to such things in my mind. It also usually means that it’s a little out of the comfort zone, just enough to create uncertainty and doubt about the outcome and my capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were attempting a hike called the R2R2R, short for Rim to Rim to Rim, in a day. It involves starting at one rim(North or South) of the canyon, hiking to the other, and then back again. It’s considered to be one of the most iconic and difficult hikes in North America. It’s about 45 mi long, with 14k feet of elevation gain and loss, and the trail, although well maintained, is rocky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people go from almost no running to running ultra-marathons in a matter of months, or take the leap from road running to trail running and crush it. Not me. I take small, incremental steps. It has taken me two years of hiking, running, and mental strengthening to get to running a 50k(32mi). I found out fairly quickly that speed isn’t my strong suit, which naturally made me switch from road racing to trail running. I also don’t do well in a competitive setting. External goals and pressures don’t motivate me. I like the idea of a personal challenge, without the fuss of a competition. That’s another reason why trail running suits me better. In other words, I’m fairly slow, not merely on the trail, but also in taking leaps of faith. What I had signed up for today though was technically not a run, more like an ultra hike. After having had one 50k under my belt from two years ago, I thought that hiking 45mi in a day probably wasn’t going to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sign on one of the windows of the bus said, “Many hikers think they are strong and attempt hikes beyond their capabilities. Don’t be one of them. Know your limits” and a whistle started to go off in my mind. It’s not like I need any real reason to go into self-doubt - my mind is happy to create reasons of its own - so this sign, to put it mildly, didn’t help calm me at that moment. Ever since I read the novel “The Alchemist’’, by Paulo Coelho, I’ve been a believer in signals of the Universe, and that it’s up to us to identify and unpack them. It’s a superstitious belief, I know, but it keeps me curious and attuned to the opportunities and warnings around me. It’s also an interesting idea because what you make of those signals tells a lot about your inner state than about the Universe. I took the sign on the bus as a warning for me to back off before I did something stupid. I felt like I was the ignorant hiker that it was referring to. As I was thinking about it, the bus dropped us at the trailhead and it was time to get off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the trailhead, I saw a few people massaging their legs,  beaten but at the same time elated and mildly proud. I knew that they had run the whole R2R2R trail - they were ultra-runners! I asked one of the guys how long it took him to do that and he said ten hours. We had given ourselves twenty-four hours. If those runners could do it in less than half that time, I thought, our goal wasn’t that too hard after all. What those runners had done made our oh-so-ambitious goal look pale in comparison. Talking to them helped because it put me in the right mindset. I felt a little more confident, more optimistic and I conveniently forgot the signal of the Universe that I was pondering a few minutes ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watched people at the trailhead, I thought that this was a gateway to a world of possibilities. Like in life, we all started at the same place, but depending on our needs, desires, experiences, and capabilities, ended up on different paths, choosing our adventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some were just happy to be there. They didn’t need anything more from it. They saw the canyons, took pictures, and enjoyed the company of their friends and family. A majority of the visitors ventured a little further to a vista point, aptly called, the “Ooh Aah Point”, which was a mile into the trail. The more adventurous ones hiked down to the river, at the bottom of the canyon, and hiked back. Some stayed there overnight, camping and enjoying the canyons and the river for a little longer.  The more capable ones hiked to the other rim, camped there, and hiked back the next day, or extended the trip to more than two days. People who were in it for the challenge of it more than anything else, hiked to the other rim and back in one stretch, either running, walking, or crawling. I was the kind who’d dream of running, start walking and end up crawling. I’m not sure what that makes me – adventurous, brave, strong, and capable, or merely a wannabe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started the hike at 06.00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had broken the hike into six sections to have a mental map of how much was done, or more importantly, of how much wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;13&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:16px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 19% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;50px&quot; height=&quot;50px&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 60 60&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; xmlns=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;none&quot; stroke-width=&quot;1&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot;&gt;&lt;g transform=&quot;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&quot; fill=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding-top: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&quot;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 12.5% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: auto;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Gaurav Ramesh | 🌿🏃🚴⛺📷 (@out.of.desk)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-1-the-trailhead-to-phantom-ranch&quot;&gt;Section 1. The Trailhead to Phantom Ranch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comprises the first seven miles of the hike, all downhill, where you lose about 5k ft in elevation until you get to the bottom of the canyon. Despite constituting about a third of the entire distance, in terms of the effort and energy needed, it’s more like a tenth. The Colorado River at the bottom, depending on the time of the year, can be spectacular scenery. We hiked at the end of April when the fresh snow melted by the early summer sun brings a loud gush of water. It was very tempting to run this section and be done as fast as I could, but I resisted giving in to that because the hike was long and hard and I wanted to save every bit of energy for the hike back and up. This was not unlike the tug of war that plays every day in our mind between instant gratification and the long-term benefits of not succumbing to its pull. The former is natural and easier to seek, but it’s the hard things that are often worth doing. Running downhill is tough on the knees too, so it was better to walk fast than run, to reduce stress on the joints. Hiking poles were helpful and acted as the extra support that we lost sometime millions of years ago when our ancestors learned to stand upright on two limbs. There was drinking water at the end of the section, so I had started merely with two bottles of water and sipped away as much as I wanted. It was already starting to get dark towards the end, but the almost full moon brought enough light to the floor of the canyon that I didn’t require headlamps. The trail was rocky, so it might not have been wise to walk partially blindly in the moonlight, but since I didn’t fall or trip, in retrospect, it now seems like a good idea to have put my visual senses and attention to use to navigate without headlamps. It was certainly unique. With more reliance on our evolutionary making and less on technology, I felt closer to our simpler, pre-modern ancestors, like I was living how we are supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-2-phantom-ranch-to-manzanita&quot;&gt;Section 2. Phantom Ranch to Manzanita&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is nine miles of almost flat trails, where you gain about 2.5k to 3k ft in elevation, and, I think, is the most comfortable section of the entire hike, at least for the legs. It’s the best chance to make up for time lost in the climbs. There was no drinking water here, but you’d be walking right along the river, so you could always filter from it if you were dying of dehydration. This section could be further divided into two, 7.5 mi to Cottonwood campground and 1.5 mi to Manzanita from there. Cottonwood usually has drinking water year-round, but it didn’t when we hiked, because of COVID-19 concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Manzanita, we found some benches, restrooms, and drinking water. It was a few minutes past midnight when we got there and my friend started to feel sleepy. Since the next section was the hardest of the whole hike, or so we thought, it seemed like a good idea to take a nap and a snack break before we continued. With just the two of us out there in the dark, I didn’t feel comfortable sleeping while he was asleep, so I stayed awake, snacking and thinking. Reflection, when not filled with negative and toxic thoughts, can be an effective antidote to boredom. You need no one and nothing else but your own company. A short nap and some caffeine seemed like a good combination for what was about to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-3-manzanita-to-the-north-rim&quot;&gt;Section 3. Manzanita to the North Rim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six miles were uphill with steep grades, all the way to the North Rim. You gain about 4k-4.5k ft in elevation. For someone who hasn’t done it before, the six miles can feel like sixteen. It just doesn’t end. Time flies, but the trail seems to not care about it. Every mile felt like two and every switchback looked like an unwelcome surprise. Around 4.30 am when we were a few miles away from the top, I looked up and saw the Milky Way. I wished I could stop to take a photo, but I neither had the patience, nor the time and energy for it. Every second was important and so was every step. I had to keep moving. The trail wasn’t going to magically slide beneath my feet. We weren’t even half the way yet. So I quietly soaked myself in the landscape for a few seconds, expressed my gratitude for the good fortune I had to be able to enjoy this, and continued climbing. At 6 am, we made it to the North Rim, exactly twelve hours after where we’d started from, which now seemed like a faraway land. There was nobody there but us. Looking at the vast canyon from that vantage point, I felt like someone who had lost contact with the civilization and was trying to find their way back home. It was cold there so we didn’t stay long. Knowing that it was six miles downhill again was comforting and helped us keep going. The day was getting brighter but the sun was still making its way above the canyons. The sun and I were fighting the same uphill battle in some ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-4-back-to-manzanita&quot;&gt;Section 4. Back to Manzanita&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from the rim, I took a ten-minute nap somewhere on the trail under the warmth of the sun, which was now up and shining in my face. In a couple of hours, we were back in Manzanita, which was now crowded, full of runners, who were making this hike look easy with their banters, laughs, and light packs. Lack of sleep that I had started increasingly feeling and the pain that started to show itself in various parts of the body made me sulk at the runners. Not that they cared, but I sulked away for my comfort. A few more snacks and some water and we took off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-5-back-to-phantom-ranch&quot;&gt;Section 5. Back to Phantom Ranch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were back on the flats again, but after twenty-eight miles into the hike and with low reserves of sleep and energy, even that felt challenging. The shoulders yelled with each step at the weight I was carrying. The back had similar complaints. I took breaks and dropped my backpack every hour in an attempt to put them at ease. But they’d scream soon as I started. There was a long way to go still, so no amount of self-pity could have helped. I had to keep moving. One of the things about putting yourself out there to suffer in nature is that it doesn’t take long to find out that it’s an unbeatable force and so your only way out is to make peace with your finiteness, and then to ask, with humility, for some mercy, and muster all the courage and will that you have. Unlike with people, when you’re up against nature, anything that happens to you is on you. It has no bias, no motives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the section was a chance to get lemonade. The store at the Phantom Ranch area was now open and serving snacks and cold drinks. The thought of an iced lemonade pushed me in the last few miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had visualized hiking this trail to mentally prepare, I had thought about all the things I’d think about during the hike but the thought about lemonade was not one of them. It’s amazing, and naive, how we think we’re in control of our thoughts, but often are nothing more than mere observers of the ones that come to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of us sipped a glass of lemonade and then I took a twenty-minute nap. It was close to 1.30 PM, I think. After the nap and some futile attempts at motivating each other, we started moving. It was close to 2.30 PM when we started towards the final leg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-6-the-final-leg---phantom-ranch-to-the-south-rim&quot;&gt;Section 6. The Final Leg - Phantom Ranch to the South Rim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was trying to avoid even thinking about this section in the hope that if I never thought about it, it’d get better. It’s this denial of reality, or rather, firm belief in the fiction that problems go away by not addressing them that turns a seemingly harmless piece of stone into an avalanche over time. We do this all the time – a difficult conversation with a friend or a colleague, or deep emotional troubles that haven’t been paid attention to – not thinking about them is one way to avoid them, and so is getting drunk, but the sooner we realize that there’s no magic the better. Acknowledgment of the problem, acceptance of reality, and the courage and willingness to face them are what make us emerge stronger. “Slow and steady”, I told myself, “and I’ll make it”. “Slow” it certainly was, not so sure about “steady”. I felt like I didn’t even care much about finishing the hike at that point, that all I wanted to do was drop the pack and be done. The only thought that pushed me was knowing that the more I slowed the worse it got. We were already cutting it pretty close to the 24-hour mark and the last shuttle ran an hour past sunset. Missing that would mean walking one more mile to the car. So one leg in front of the other and I kept moving. At 7.30 pm, 25.5 hours after I had started, I dropped dead back at the trailhead, pale, sunburnt, and with no juice left in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We caught the shuttle back to the car, cooked and ate dinner before heading to the campsite. Once at the campsite, we went straight into our sleeping bags, only to see each other the next morning. We packed our stuff, took shower at the Tusayan General Store, which lets you soak in hot water for eight minutes per token, and started to drive back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reflections-on-the-way-back-home&quot;&gt;Reflections on the way back home&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental preparation is key for such challenges. If someone asked me to walk 47 miles on city streets, I’d gladly reject the offer. I’d say that I could not physically do it, but I’d be lying. The truth is that it’d mentally bore the heck out of me, and that belief will make sure that I give up, well before I reach my physical limits. It was the magnificence of the canyon, the respect this hike commanded, and the reputation it had, that helped me view this as a challenge worth pursuing. Rather than spending weeks leading up to the hike physically training, I visualized myself being on foot in the canyons for 24 hours without sleep and food. Of course, I didn’t know how it’d feel like, because I hadn’t done it before, but it helped me get familiar with the idea of walking for that long. I went over the uphills, the downhills, and the flats of the trail repeatedly while staring at the maps, telling myself that it wasn’t that bad. I educated myself about the hydration and fueling strategies and convinced myself that I’d take them seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of it was as I’d imagined it to be. The landscape was more beautiful than the canyons of my imagination, the downhills were harder on the knees than I thought, and the uphill was more brutal than I prepared mentally for. Shoulders and back hurt more than the legs which came as a total surprise. As far as fueling goes, it turns out that when the body is in pain and discomfort, it rejects food, and so the twelve pounds of the backpack I chugged the whole way, like a mule, was for nothing. I had downloaded audiobooks and motivational podcasts into my phone to listen to when things got harder, but I learned that no amount of external motivation can make up for the lack of internal drive. It’s only when I talked myself into putting one leg in front of the other did I make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While climbing up the North Rim, less than halfway through the hike, I kept telling myself that I had reached my limit. The line from the sign came roaring back to me.. “Don’t be one of them.. Know your limits”. It was interesting how every step, after a point, felt like the last step I could take, but somehow every step convinced me that I could take one more. The concept of limit seemed plastic. The more I stretched it, the more it kept stretching, without snapping, which tells me that the limits that we think are physical, in most cases, are in the mind. The quote I read somewhere now makes sense, “The mind always gives up before the body”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the hike, when I was telling my friends and family that my legs felt relatively good, and that the back and shoulders were doing much worse, I learned something insightful. My legs were ready for the distance. Had I dropped my pack and went light, with a bottle of water and some snacks, I could have done it much faster and the experience would have been much smoother. Running the trail somehow started to look doable. I told myself that I was going to attempt running it the following year. I also realized that my legs would have been okay walking a few more miles, which tells me that 65 mi, i.e. 100k is well within reach, of course, with some physical and mental training. That’d be the next formidable challenge worth chasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the activity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/5191472030&quot;&gt;Strava&lt;/a&gt;, for the curious ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/hiking/reflections/endurance/2021/05/03/grand-canyon-r2r2r.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/hiking/reflections/endurance/2021/05/03/grand-canyon-r2r2r.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
        <category>endurance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Runs in Thoughts in Runs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was young, my mom, my brother and I used to make at least two trips every summer. One was to my maternal grandparents’ place and one to my paternal ones’. The places and the experiences from the two couldn’t have been more different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal grandparents’ home was a relatively comfortable place in an old cotton mill town and, as far as we were concerned, had all the comforts and luxuries that we wanted – new clothes that mom would buy for us, theaters to watch the latest movies with our uncles, good restaurants to be treated with the best food in town, and street food to test the limits of our young bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paternal grandparents lived in a small village, in a place beside the areca and coconut farms that we owned, with my dad’s younger brother and his wife. My dad had left the village when he was young, against his father’s liking, and had moved to town to make a better living. They hardly ever spoke eye to eye after that. The admiration and love they had for each other hadn’t gone down, but the damage done to the male egos never completely healed, I think. None of us ever talked about it. We were too young then, and it’s too late now. I can only surmise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a humble living in the village, with no dearth of love and affection, but only of the material things. In summer there were power outages that spanned days, sometimes weeks, at a stretch, with nothing much to do. We had a few cows and calves, and a couple of cats and dogs. Feeding them, cuddling them and walking them around was what we did for entertainment. It later turned into a hobby. Every morning we went to take a dip in a nearby stream right in front of the village temple, a short walk from our home. The time we spent in the village has been, in retrospect, more memorable than the city life we lived for the majority of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water in the stream was usually clear, cold, and ankle-deep during the summer; the bottom rugged and rocky.  Adults helped us cross the stream when we were little. As we grew older, we got more able and independent. We had learned the necessary skills to make our way across without tripping or falling in water. Rarely do we now encounter such intimate moments with nature, but when we do it’s a rewarding experience. As we made it past childhood to adulthood, we comfortably crossed not merely the stream, but also the thin line between confidence and arrogance. What we once viewed as a force of nature to be admired, and regarded, became dull, inconsequential, and even inconvenient. Thanks to climate change, the force really did decline, with the amount of water now hardly enough to fill an aquarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That arrogance seems to be an unfortunate truth, not merely of individuals, but of our species as a whole. We think we are the ones in charge, not only of our lives, but of everything around us. We think that we possess the capacity to bend the world to our will, rather than being good citizens of the planet with a fair share of compromises to make and fulfilling our obligations towards it. We forget that while we might have the ability to choose our actions, we’re not in control of the outcomes, that they are up to the forces external to us, and bigger, more powerful than us. The rocks underneath, going back to those streams, could be slippery, and the water turbulent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are all kinds of things that could go wrong in the space that exists between our actions and the outcomes of it. If nothing does, well, we do what we do best, pat ourselves on the back and move on with our smugness unshaken, or emboldened. It’s those of us who experience helplessness and vulnerability in the face of a challenge too big to overcome who often possess the humility and grace to accept the truth of our fallibility, limits and weaknesses, and of our place in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, when I had these recollections, I had a weird and amusing thought. I wondered if I was crossing the river while it was flowing, or if the river was flowing while I was crossing. It was a fleeting thought and I didn’t heed to it much at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days after, while I was running, I found myself pondering over a similar thought, in a different setting. I found myself asking if I think while running or run while thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar..how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was crossing the stream of thoughts on foot, running, rather than walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts, like a stream of water, are perennially flowing, and perpetually changing their course. Running, on the other hand, is deliberate and has a concrete start and stop to it. I guess there’s a philosophical argument that can be made that in some sense we’re all running towards something all the time, but that’s not the kind of running I’m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I’d like my thinking also to be deliberate, I find out every time that thoughts can neither be summoned nor be directed at will. Well, I guess that’s not completely true. When we have control over the mind, we can, but when we gain control of the mind is not up to us. It’s dictated by the mind itself. So it’s not as much as taking control, as it is accepting it, when it’s relinquished by our mind. The mind has its hierarchy of needs. When the base ones have been met, it lets you focus on things that are, while important, matter the least, relatively speaking. The less turbulent it is, the better your chances of being able to exercise your will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I start running, for example, the first few thoughts are about how my body is feeling. I can’t help it. They just occur to me. This is what I call the “safety system” talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are my glutes too tight?&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Are my knees hurting?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Is my back too stiff?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Is my form proper?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re followed by thoughts about the logistics of the run. This is the “optimization system” doing its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I going too fast, or slow?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How long do I want to run?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How long can I comfortably run, considering how much I ran yesterday?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How much do I plan to run the rest of the week?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What do I listen to?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do I have my tracker on?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running pace dictates how clearly I can think. Run too fast and the “safety system” kicks in, taking control back. Run too slow and the “optimization system” takes charge. The pace has to be in a sweet spot where both the systems are content and quiet. That pace is different for everybody, and it changes over time and with context. I think that’s true not merely with running, but with life. We all have a pace we’re comfortable with and goals we aspire to, but knowing what they are takes time and deliberate effort. When I’m training for a race, I will want to be more mindful about the pace, when I’m running to get over a hard, or bad, day, I don’t care as much, when I’m running to think, I might run slower than usual. My pace is probably faster than some, and slower than a lot of other people, but as long as I’m enjoying the run and it’s serving the purpose I run for, it doesn’t matter much. When you find the pace you’re comfortable with, you hit a rhythm, at which point keeping one leg in front of the other becomes as mechanical as pedaling a bike. Depending on how you’re feeling and the amount of gas left in you, that repetition can go on for as long as you want. That’s when the mind decides that it’s okay for you to take over and focus on what you want to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about thinking, “shower thoughts” come to mind. People often stumble upon good ideas while taking a shower. I do, too. But I feel like the five or ten minutes it takes me to finish one is not long enough to think through those ideas. It doesn’t provide me the continuity required to go deep into anything, unless, of course, I stay there long enough to let the hot water wash away not merely the dirt, but peel my skin along with it. Shower thoughts make for a good tweet. They can be smart, creative, funny, or even profound. Like people scrolling endlessly on the Internet glancing at posts and moving on, so do you — you mentally “like” the idea, feel good about yourself and move on to the next thought. There’s no dearth of such shower thoughts to scroll through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the few times in the day I get uninterrupted alone time long enough to think through things is while running. It also makes it conducive to focus so I can dig into the thoughts, peel the layers, connect different ideas and organize them. It gives me the space and resources to play with the Lego blocks that are thoughts and build a concrete, stable structure out of them. It helps me better understand myself and the world around me. Thoughts on a run make for good long-form writing, and I say good, not in a pompous way, but rather with a humble realization that the amount of attention involved stands to benefit you in more than one way. At worst, you’ll have spent time trying to understand the nuances of things, and you’ll have emerged having learned something. At best, you’ll have created something that others will find value in and will pay for with their time and attention, which is as valuable a currency as one can hope for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned from running that it matters more that you run, than where and when you do. So while I still don’t have an answer to the question I started with, the inquiry proved more useful than where I ended up with it. I now know more about the thoughts I have while running and I know that as long as I’m exercising my mental and physical muscles, I’m making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/running/thoughts/2021/04/02/runs-in-thoughts-in-runs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/running/thoughts/2021/04/02/runs-in-thoughts-in-runs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>running</category>
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Old Memory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day, I remember, as I was riding in the back of my colleague’s motorbike, in some of the fancy neighborhoods of Bangalore. I don’t even remember his full name. We called him &lt;em&gt;Khan Sir&lt;/em&gt;. You didn’t have to have knighthood to be addressed as &lt;em&gt;Sir&lt;/em&gt; in India. It was merely a sign of respect, a polite acknowledgement of your age, knowledge or experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was about a week after our CEO told us that we were shutting down due to lack of sufficient funding. This was a perfect opportunity for the entrepreneurial-minded, and Khan Sir was one. He had an idea that he wanted to work on, to try and make a product, and eventually a company, out of it. He had always wanted to give it a shot, but the resistance that comes from comfort and a fat paycheck can be hard to battle. This was the window and the push he was secretly wishing for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wanted a dummy to turn his idea into a working prototype. I was willing to help, a young and naively energetic and optimistic engineer, trying to grab every opportunity that presented itself. I was waiting to fly to the US for my Master’s degree in a few months, so I had nothing to lose if this little tinkering didn’t work, and something to gain if it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After building an MVP, we traveled on his motorbike to pitch the idea to potential investors. That’s when I first visited some of the rich homes of the Silicon Valley of India. These were the people that made it all happen. They listened to people all day long, sifted through the pile of ideas and the list of people with ideas, and funded the ones that they thought had the potential to make it big. We sure thought we were one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those brief rounds with Khan Sir taught me more about him, his motivations and aspirations than a year working with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the stops we made, we parked the bike right next to a dog that was sleeping on the street. Our arrival was an unwelcome change in his world. How do I know? His face told us that. Turns out animals are good at communicating non-verbal clues. At least that was my interpretation of it. I would have been pissed if somebody woke me up from my mid-day nap. I guess that tells more about me than what the dog was &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I suppose he didn’t know, or care, that it was mid-day, or even mid-week. It’s not like he had some place he’d rather be, or something he’d rather be doing. He was right where he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to be, precisely when he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to be, doing exactly what he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to do. He probably also didn’t have any cultural notions about what he ought to do with his life. That seems like something only animals as smart as us could come up with, and then brood over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts about meaning and purpose, of why we are here, consumes most of us at various points in our life. Sometimes so much that it pushes us over the edge of uncertainty and leaves us rolling down helplessly and endlessly because the answers don’t come easy. It dictates, consciously or not, things we do with our time, and hence with our lives. Different cultures and societies, as do different individuals, have different ideas about them. For some, it’s about pleasing God, or working towards a divine reward. For others, it’s about living a good life, whatever that means, a life of virtues and principles, perhaps. For some, it’s the pursuit of knowledge, and for others, it’s about finding their true potential, exploring the limits of their body and mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the dog. There was something very peaceful about the way he was sleeping amidst all the noise around him. For a moment, I felt like trading lives with him. As I was thinking it, Khan sir interrupted my chain of thought and said something along the same lines. He said he’d have preferred to be born as a dog, so that he didn’t have to worry about building a company, or about finding meaning in life. He felt like trading lives with the dog too! The zen-like state that the dog was projecting, of being able to tune out the external noises and the internal voices and being completely immersed in what he enjoyed was enviable. It’s what we all strive to achieve, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted the dog’s life because I was lazy. I’d rather be sleeping than working. But for him, it was deeper than that. He was, I now realize, dealing with the dichotomy of pain and pleasure that comes from being driven. Internal drive, just like external ones, can be ruthless at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had a wife and a kid. His wife was pregnant at the time with the second one and had gone to her mother’s place for six months. So he had given himself six months to work on his idea. He had saved enough to make it work, without work. It’s kind of a short deadline though, and a hard one, knowing that you got half a year to turn the abstract in your mind into something concrete in the real world, and knowing that this was one of those rare moments when things fall into place to open a narrow window of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His passion to make an impact in the world was pushing him towards something that was hard and uncomfortable yet rewarding at the same time. He felt the agony of spending all that time away from his kid and his then-pregnant wife, of life slipping away from his hands without him being present with his loved ones, but also experienced the joy that comes from attending to the calling from within. He’d have preferred an easier life if he could, but his drive left him no choice. I learned recently that that idea or state is explained through the concept of positive liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I couldn’t empathize with him. I wasn’t passionate about anything, and I didn’t have responsibilities of anyone but my own. Time, as far as I was concerned, was a perennial resource. I had the majority of my life ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was in the year 2013, which seems like a long time ago now. The memory of this whole episode kept coming back to me at various times, in different situations, years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, in 2016, when I started to become interested in outdoor activities and got into running, hiking, and biking, I remember how I couldn’t get myself to do anything during the weekends but that. The rush and excitement was irresistible. Friday evening, I hit the road, only to be back home on Sunday. Every weekend a new destination, with new people. Even my day job took a backseat for a while. I focused less on my career and more on such experiences. With this new found freedom, I thought, and read, a lot about balance and free will but at the same time felt completely helpless in the grips of the inner force that was controlling me. It occurred to me how he, or most entrepreneurs, must feel like when they invest all their precious resources – time, money, and energy – into building something, knowing well that the chances of it going anywhere good are rather slim. It’s hard to tell if it’s what you are choosing to do, or if it’s the inner voice making you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, in 2021, while sitting on a couch dragging my fingers against the iPad screen, looking for e-books in my library app, I stumbled upon a book called &lt;em&gt;“How to Teach Philosophy to Your Dog - Exploring the Big Questions in Life”&lt;/em&gt;, by Anthony McGowan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title piqued my interest for two reasons: first, because of my interest in books that break down complex subjects into simple language, and second, because I was curious about how ideas from a subject, as complex and as abstract as Philosophy, could possibly be transported out of the realm of human understanding and extended to a dog’s world. The title also brought back that old memory and for a moment, my mind drifted away…wondering about that dog…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was he still alive? What would he be doing with his life now, if he were?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over all these years, would he have grown in some way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did old age teach him lessons he would tell his younger self? All those days spent sleeping, could they have been spent any better, in a more productive way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and wondering about freedom…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was the dog freer than us, in a way, without being constantly crippled by the worries in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is free will and freedom reflected in what we do, or what we &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is the latter, are we &lt;em&gt;choosing&lt;/em&gt; to do the things we do in our life, or are we merely telling ourselves that to be able to sleep at night? If we’re acting purely and solely based on our impulses, are we even exercising our freedom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07VS3WFK2/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;How to Teach Philosophy to Your Dog: Exploring the Big Questions in Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/liberty-positive-negative/&quot;&gt;Positive and Negative Liberty: Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/philosophy/meaning/passion/2021/02/28/an-old-memory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/philosophy/meaning/passion/2021/02/28/an-old-memory.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>meaning</category>
        
        <category>passion</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>About Simple and Obvious Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One afternoon at work I had a meeting to release the last piece of a project that was meant to change the way our clients interacted with the backend systems. It was a fairly simple routing change at the load balancer and was expected to be done in a few minutes. Not all people invited were strictly required in the meeting, so while a few joined, others kept an eye on their respective systems for any potential misbehaviours and followed a Slack channel for constant updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, talking with a few people on the video call, and texting a couple more on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five minutes into the meeting, we did the change and shifted our attention to the monitoring systems to see early signs of success, or to minimize damage in the remote possibility of a failure. Twenty minutes later, we still didn’t see any activity that we’d expected or hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the change was such that it was expected to take a short period to propagate but we didn’t know, or could tell, how long exactly. So we didn’t sweat. We had theories about why it might be taking longer than usual. About thirty minutes later, we decided to involve somebody from the iOS team to simulate tests from the clients’ perspective to get some validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They took their sweet time to prepare their devices and simulators for the test. After about fifteen minutes, we finally tested it and saw some errors. When we dug into it, we learned that our customers had been seeing those errors in Production all this time since I made the change about fifty minutes ago! What was weird was that no whistles and bells went off, no pages were triggered, so, for a moment, we doubted if the customers did, in fact, have any negative impact. In any case, we reverted the change, just to be safe. The errors, as you’d guess, went away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first learned about the impact of the incident, I felt embarrassed and a little nervous. For how business-critical this was, fifty minutes was enternity! We should have known long before that. But the guilt and embarrasment was not because it could have been avoided — that realization only came later — but because I instantly started questioning my abilities. I was trusted with it, and I was incapable of executing it. It was my lack of knowledge and technical skill, I thought, that was the problem, and my self-doubt started to eat me up. To calm down the inner voice, I even went into denial and started blaming other people for it, at least in my mind, if not in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it was all dealt with, my manager called me on my phone to have a chat. He was kind and responsible enough to reflect on it and think of ways he could have helped me. But there was one thing he mentioned which guided my thinking in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asked me what my plan was before I got into the meeting. How dare he ask me what the plan was, I thought. Was he hinting that I didn’t or doubting if I had a plan at all? I obviously had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into the meeting assuming that I knew all that had to be done, and I didn’t anticipate anything going wrong. Saying that I didn’t anticipate is an understatement. I was so confident that nothing would go wrong that I didn’t consider any options for when it did go wrong. It wasn’t a gap in my knowledge that was the problem, but lack of thought and foresight, about the potential consequences and impact of the change on the system as a whole, both good and bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many pieces to this change and even though each one of those was fairly simple, they had to be executed in a specific order, and more importantly every one of those was cruicial to the success. And because of their fragmented nature, it was really easy to miss a couple of steps and roll down the metaphorical stairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atul Gawande, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right/dp/0312430000&quot;&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right&lt;/a&gt;, mentions an essay from the 1970s by philosophers Samuel Gorovitz and Alasdair MacIntyre, which talks about human fallibility. One reason they talk about for why things go wrong is “necessary fallibility”, which is when they’re beyond our capacity to control. These, by definition, can’t be prevented from happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he identifies two other reasons — &lt;em&gt;ignorance&lt;/em&gt;, the gaps in our knowledge, and &lt;em&gt;ineptitude&lt;/em&gt;, our failure to apply the knowledge correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignorance, if we’re willing to learn, can be reduced over time; the more time we put into something, the more we learn about it, the more knowledge we gain. But competence is something that doesn’t build over time. Getting rid of ineptitude, in other words, building competence, requires discipline, patience, and deliberate practice. In fact, there’s a case to be made that the more knowledge we possess, the more likely it is to blind ourselves to a holistic, systems thinking approach unless we’re constantly reevaluating ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having the necessary knowledge to execute the task at hand, I had failed to come up with a plan, a checklist of things that I should have had in place before I jumped on it. But my mistake had a meta nature to it. I knew the importance of checklists, but had failed to put that knowledge too, which made me aware of the difference between theory and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the incident, I finally started taking the idea of checklists, the habit of note-taking, seriously. I especially note things that seem simple and obvious, because those are the ones that are likely to be missed, by everybody. If there’s one thing I’ve learned from my experience is that things that seem simple and obvious, are not necessarily easy and not so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Avoidable failures are common and persistent, not to mention demoralizing and frustrating, across many fields -- from medicine to finance, business to government. And the reason is increasingly evident: the volume and complexity of what we know has exceeded our individual ability to deliver its benefits correctly, safely, or reliably. Knowledge has both saved us and burdened us.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right/dp/0312430000&quot;&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/work/productivity/learning/note-taking/2020/06/27/simple-and-obvious.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/work/productivity/learning/note-taking/2020/06/27/simple-and-obvious.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>work</category>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        <category>note-taking</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Chat With the Different Selfs</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We all have various sides of our self, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about how the pandemic has affected me, I can’t think of one absolute way it has. The experience hasn’t been binary, one that can be categorized into good or bad. We all have various sides of our &lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to think about what those are for me, bring them to light, and get them to talk. Most of them have adapted quite well to the changes necessitated by the constraints of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-different-selfs&quot;&gt;The different selfs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we spend a better part of our lives doing our day job, it naturally defines us in a significant way, if not completely. I work as a software engineer, and it’s one of my important identities, it’s also the one that’s most visible or known to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the integral parts of my job, an activity that is also close to my heart, is to always keep learning. That’s another thing I identify myself with - as someone eager to learn and open to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental, and in some ways more important, part of my identity is one that’s obsessed with practising a healthy lifestyle. I say important because I believe it nourishes the other selfs, and fundamental because it’s less fluid in nature than the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other important dimension is the part of me that cares deeply about animals. I say &lt;em&gt;cares&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt;, because that’s an important distinction, and even though I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; some animals, I want to be mindful about the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one other aspect of me has stood the test of time. I don’t have much control over it, and I’ve had a love-hate relationship with it, more hate than love - my introverted nature. More hate than love because I’ve only recently started to accept, and nurture it, rather than treating it like a problem that needed fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next one is a close kin of the self that wants to lead a healthy life, but is more opinionated on how to go about it. It believes in spending time in nature, and doing physically challenging things to keep the body and the mind in good shape. The curious and learning part of me constantly feeds this self, with new ideas, challenges to tackle and goals to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one I can think of is the most volatile of them all, and has only come to consciousness very recently. It swims up to the surface and goes back to hiding depending on the things that’s happening around me - the one that thinks of itself as an immigrant in a foreign country, a guest in someone else’s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I try to prod each one of them to express their thoughts about how they feel being sheltered in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-a-software-engineer&quot;&gt;As a software engineer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s fairly easy to work remotely and still be productive. While I miss the walks and talks around the office with my peers to get coffee during the day, I’ve made up for it by experimenting with different kinds of plant-based milk coffees at home. After several weeks of trial-and-error, it’s getting close to my liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate that wifi at home is not as good and causes, part frustrating, part funny, technical issues while talking to my colleagues on video calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also miss the desk setup and multiple monitors I used to have in the office, but for now, I’m managing with an REI camp chair, a laptop and a monitor. It’s easy to get lost in work and forget how or where I’m sitting at home. Stiffness from bad body postures used to be a problem in the first weeks, but I’ve gotten more mindful about that over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/engineer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to wait for meeting rooms to free up to chat with people - they’re just a few clicks and a video call away. I think it’s more productive and collaborative than an open-office setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to rush to catch the train and sit through a long commute to get to work in the morning, and that I can start working early in the day when my mind is at its best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first few weeks, I worked more than usual, and so did my peers. But I’ve gotten better at drawing boundaries between work and personal life, even without a physical one separating the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing I don’t miss is the incessant chatter in the office, where unnecessary small talk is confused with collaboration and coding is confused with mindless typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the things I don’t miss from going to work and the things I love about working from home, I’d do more remote work going forward for sure, and hope companies embrace it more too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-avid-reader&quot;&gt;As an avid reader,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that the two or more hours I used to spend riding in train to go to work, I now spend riding in train of thoughts, one that takes me to farther and better places. Reading not only helps me unplug from the stress and concerns of work, but the comfort and peace of doing it from home improves my mood. The absence of distractions of a typical workday has helped me do more of a fewer things rather than juggle a little bit of everything. Long stretches of undistracted time allows me to focus on reading books, long-form articles and write more, rather than filling the tiny slices of time over the day with news and junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absence or lack of something usually makes you realize its importance, but it’s interesting in a way that having more, and not less, time in hand has made me realize how much of it was being taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/reading.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also starting to see the benefits of consistency and discipline, of cultivating enough patience to do something everyday despite the initial aversion and resistance, and how it can make a big difference relatively quickly. Though I have been trying to get into the habit of writing for over a year, I’ve only been this consistent and serious about it since I started working from home. The world had to hit brakes on its operations and get rid of distractions for me to start writing. It’s like the Universe really wanted to teach me good habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-outdoor-enthusiast&quot;&gt;As an outdoor enthusiast,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really worried about not being able to travel. I had a few races that I had signed up for and a few trips I had planned for this year. But sitting at home, not having hiked or biked in a couple of months now has taught me that I don’t need to go to new places to freshen up my mind, or to enjoy outdoors every time I head out. That I can just step out of the door and start running until I get tired and run back. That it can be that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started running a couple of years ago for the fun of it, and maybe a little to lose weight too, but over time, I started getting obsessed over quantifying the benefits of every activity - the calories burnt, pounds lost, and speed etc,. I’m now back to those simple days. Not every run now goes in Strava, not every race has to end up in PRs, not every walk now is a hike and not every bike ride is captured in photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/outdoor.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solace I used to find in the outdoors, I’ve found it in reading and writing too. Although there is something magical about being out in nature, I realize that one of the reasons it felt so good was the time it gave me to pause, and reflect on things. Turns out books do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-introvert&quot;&gt;As an introvert,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m in love with the silence. It not only helps me think clearly, and be more productive at work, it also puts me in a much better mood overall. Even after working long hours, I find that I have the time and energy to go on walks with my wife, cook, go for a run, read, write and talk to friends and family on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/introvert.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the idea of minimizing sounds that fall in my ears, the idea of letting them in willingly rather than being bombarded with unnecessary and unsolicited noises all day long and being forcefully made a passive member in every conversation around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-immigrant&quot;&gt;As an immigrant&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from India, I see the contrast in how people from the two countries are reacting to the pandemic, both common people and those in power. Being from the majority group in India, and a part of one of the minority groups(immigrants) here in the US, it gives some perspectives on how stereotypes and misinformation against minorities are used for political and capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’m concerned about the well-being of older members of my family back home and wish I were there, a part of me feels relieved that I’m not with them to inadvertently infect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/immigrant.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see through the lies and the facade of developed societies and feel hopeful and optimistic, to see the potential of the developing nations and their simple, yet effective ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the things that have worked for countries and things that haven’t, I realize that more technology is not necessarily the right solution to all problems. Common sense and empirical evidence are perfectly fine at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-animal-rights-believer&quot;&gt;As an animal rights believer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that non-humans have started to come out of hiding and are doing so without the fear of us harming, or killing them, that at least for a little while they regain their rights over the resources of this planet, and not everything they consume are left-overs from humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/animals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m terribly sad and shocked by the fate of hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of animals in factory farms that were killed because humans couldn’t afford to raise and kill them to eat. I can’t decide which is worse, simply killing them, or killing to eat them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that meat substitutes are seeing tremendous growth and hope that the trend continues long after our lives get back to &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt;. Although it’s a result of shortage of meat in markets right now, I hope that reduced meat and dairy consumption becomes the new normal, and people see it for what it actually is, and the problems it puts us into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slow-life-vs-fast-life&quot;&gt;Slow life vs fast life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say the world has slowed down during the pandemic, but what does it mean to be slow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we truly slowed now, or were we unnecessarily fast before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was the rush anyway, and where were we all headed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were we navigating towards a perceived sense of growth and success, or were we merely racing towards a mountain of problems created by our own greed and speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the rush was in fact necessary, why does slow feel better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the age of mind and innovation, than of body and physical labor, then why were cruising in autopilot, without stopping to think about the destination?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that the fast life we chose in pursuit of something good only made us more miserable and unhealthy, and this life of nothingness is making us happier, and healthier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that we’re regaining the connections we had lost, by distancing ourselves? That we had to be physically social-distanced to close the mental and emotional gap between each other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas and learnings from a lot of reading and collaboration between multiple dimensions of my self has gone into producing this. Of all the news and information that’s out there about the pandemic, a majority of them either portray humans as the victims, not the villains, or blame a specific section of people for all the problems. With such lopsided, and biased opinions floating around, this one below stands out with a different perspective on things and makes for a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I’ve come to shut down the machine whose emergency brake you couldn’t find
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lundi.am/What-the-virus-said&quot;&gt;What the virus said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reflection/self/pandemic/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reflection/self/pandemic/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflection</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>pandemic</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fine Walls</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been more than a month since my wife and I started working from home and about a month since our county placed the shelter-in-place in effect. Our outdoor trips are limited to walk in the evenings, and grocery shopping once a week. The rules and recommendations around the importance and usefulness of everybody wearing a mask are shifting by the day, from being useless one day to being essential the next. That, mixed with the concern of shortage of masks for healthcare workers has caused a surge in videos teaching people how to make DIY masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we went grocery shopping today, the best we could do was use scarves as masks. I realized that there’s something about hiding my face in public that made me feel uncomfortable. Not that it’s a bad idea in these times, but it still feels weird nonetheless, especially the first few times. Maybe it’s a cultural thing or availability bias that has rooted this idea in our minds that bad guys do that - people looting a bank cover their faces, terrorists cover their faces. Sure, doctors and nurses wear masks too, but the human brain doesn’t surface such images when we think about people hiding behind masks. And since face is such a crucial part of our identity, hiding it equates to hiding one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wore the scarf around my face, I also thought about how anti-social it makes us seem. Even in a country like the US, where people try to and encourage minding their business and where people try their best to avoid making accidental eye contact with strangers, wearing a mask seems especially anti-social in some way. It puts a physical boundary between two identities and hence makes the distance between us more real, one that already currently exists but is otherwise invisible. With a mask, you now don’t need to fear awkward eye contact with strangers or running into someone you know but don’t want to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t be surprised if a majority of people here will continue to wear masks after this, not for the fear of infection, but for the liberty to be themselves in public. It’s ironic then that wearing a mask will give us the liberty to throw away the mask of social identity. It looks like a way to disable one of the primary ways we communicate with each other, a way to bring anonymity offered by the Internet out into the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar boundary was drawn not too long ago, to block one of our other primary channels of communication. When I started my first job out of school a few years ago in India, every employee had their cubicle to work. It indicated a piece of space in a huge commercial floor plan which you could call your private little corner. When I got back into the workforce two years later, after attending graduate school, those boundaries were gone, or so I thought. While the idea of open office floor plans was to encourage people to be more social, I learned about the existence of a relatively new, unacknowledged, or rather differently advertised boundary, which wasn’t as far as the walls of cubicles but much closer to us - the headphones. Just like the walls of our homes which signal the borders separating our family from the outside world, headphones draw a boundary between the sounds and voices we &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to let in and everything else. With the introduction of designer and handy AirPods, that boundary has become more commonplace and prevalent and has jumped out of the confinement of the walls of office space. It’s now everywhere – on the trains, on a run, even while having lunch. I can’t help but think and feel bad about the fact that there’s tons of money to be made in the future from the fear we’re now living in and that those solutions will make us, incrementally and permanently, more distant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/society/culture/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/society/culture/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>society</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Summary: Behind the Smiles by Reveal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In March 2014 when I got an offer from Amazon for a summer internship, I couldn’t have been happier. I was happy for two reasons, one, because I needed a break from interviewing and two because it was Amazon. I didn’t know which team I was going to be working with at the time and only a few weeks before my internship, I learned that I was matched with Labor Optimization Team in Amazon Fulfillment Technologies(AFT) org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job as an intern in the team was to help build systems to make sense of the data and the models designed to analyze it by the data scientist we had. There was a lot of data about the workers working in the Fulfillment Centers, like their smoking habits, for example, and one of the goals of the team was to be able to learn and predict characteristics of people that made them stick to the job and bring down the attrition rate. I had heard how people moved in and out of these jobs and how it was hard to find workers who stayed. I didn’t think much about why that was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make us better at our jobs and help us understand the whole process, we were even flown to a Fulfillment Center during the internship. I forgot which one it was, but it had Kiva robots to move the big racks around. It was amazing to see how robots were serving humans here, doing the laborious task of carrying heavy boxes for long distances in these gigantic warehouses. Never thought about what happened after the robots brought those boxes to humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following is a summary of the article reported by Reveal on the conditions of workers at Amazon Fulfillment Centers and the cost of the ever-increasing speed of home delivery. Read on for my highlights and key takeaways from the article. You can find the original article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.revealnews.org/article/behind-the-smiles&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Injury rates are extremely high in Amazon Fulfillment Centers(warehouses). Serious injuries, which require time off from work, are double the industry average in warehouses. In some fulfillment centers and in certain times of the year, it is up to four to even six times the industry average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracking system for each of the task – pick, stow, pack and so on are immensely efficient and fierce. Scanners have to scan an item about every 11 seconds. Pickers are required to pick about 385 small or 350 medium boxes every hour. They get written up and eventually terminated for even 98.5% efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warehouses with robots are worse for workers since the expectations from them go higher when the robots get faster and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job advertisements don’t mention any skills or experience required, but the training is insufficient and expectations sky-high, when they actually start working. Holidays and peak seasons are the worst when a huge number of temporary, seasonal workers are hired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workers are too afraid of termination and retaliation to even talk about their issues or take restroom breaks. All their breaks are rigorously tracked and marked “time-off task” and their pleas fall into deaf ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some report that they had to pee in bottles, or take packages to restrooms with them to avoid missing the quota. Some have suffered urinary tract infections from holding it in for long times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of the death of a worker in Indiana operating a forklift in the warehouse was covered up and people investigating pushed back by the higher officials all the way up to the Mayor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t help but draw parallels between the almost robotic efficiency expected from humans in these warehouses to slaughterhouses in factory farms. The ever-increasing demand for stuff(packages and meat) has pushed industries to meet it at the expense of human, animal and planet health. It’s a classic case of human greed and indifference taking a toll on anyone and anything that’s poor, vulnerable and helpless. I won’t be surprised if companies like Amazon go as far to use its power and influence to get something like the ag-gag laws passed to make it illegal to record in any form the conditions of workers in its Fulfillment Centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some similarities between the two industries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both are driven by the need for speed and increased demand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers in both the industries suffer a lot more serious injuries than the industry average in jobs requiring physical labor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers in both the industries have reported not being sent to a doctor by their on-site medical staff even after multiple reports of pain and injuries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workers sometimes are told not to use unplanned restroom breaks, and other times they don’t do it out of fear of missing their quota. Some have reported using adult diapers, or peeing in a bottle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Products from the industries are eventually shipped in boxes and wrappers with smiles on them, which is utter disinformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;highlights&quot;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The clock was always ticking on Amazon’s promised delivery time. Dixon had to scan a new item every 11 seconds to hit her quota, she said, and Amazon always knew when she didn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…in the last holiday season, they hit a coveted target: They got a million packages out the door in 24 hours. Amazon handed out T-shirts celebrating their induction into the “Million Unit Club.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“An Amazon-approved doctor said she had bulging discs and diagnosed her with a back sprain, joint inflammation and chronic pain, determining that her injuries were 100% due to her job.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the rate of serious injuries for those facilities was more than double the national average for the warehousing industry: 9.6 serious injuries per 100 full-time workers in 2018, compared with an industry average that year of 4.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson said Amazon’s injury rates are high because it’s aggressive about recording worker injuries and cautious about allowing injured workers to return to work before they’re ready.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When a gas leak inundated the Eastvale warehouse where Dixon used to work, managers wouldn’t slow down, several workers said, even though they were dizzy and vomiting. They were told that they’d have to use personal time off if they wanted to leave.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the holiday season, “…warehouses are crammed with seasonal workers unaccustomed to the grind. The company’s 2018 logs show weekly injury counts spiked at two distinct moments when Amazon offers special deals: Cyber Monday and Prime Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson, the Amazon spokesperson, said total injuries do go up during those peak times, but that’s only because the company brings on more workers then.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But injury records and interviews with three of the former Amazon safety managers suggest the introduction of the robots led to even more injuries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““Before robots, it was still tough, but it was manageable,” he said. Afterward, “we were in a fight that we just can’t win.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The U.S. Department of Labor under the Obama administration proposed posting them online, but under President Donald Trump, the agency has reversed course and also has fought public records requests. And Amazon has resisted making its own safety records public.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He said higher-ups instructed him to come up with justifications for not recording injuries that should have been counted by law.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…Terry showed up for work and was sent to do maintenance on a forklift. He walked under the machine’s forks and metal platform to work on it with a wrench. Suddenly, the 1,200-pound piece of equipment dropped down and crushed him.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Stallone repeatedly pressed Amazon to provide records showing Terry had been trained on that piece of equipment. In the end, he found that Amazon failed to provide adequate training, exposing Terry to a fatal hazard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During the call, Alexander told the Amazon officials what she’d need from them in order to shift the blame from the company to “employee misconduct,” according to the recording.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Holcomb told him how much it would mean to Indiana if the state won the Amazon headquarters deal. Then, Stallone said, the commissioner told him to back off on the Amazon case – or resign.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A year after Terry’s death, Indiana officials quietly signed an agreement with Amazon to delete all the safety citations and fines. The agreement said Amazon had met the requirements of an “unpreventable employee misconduct defense.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““If there was any misconduct there, it’s putting a person that has little to no experience and working on this piece of equipment,” said the other former safety manager, who has worked at multiple facilities. “Whoever allowed that to happen – that’s the misconduct.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…had been smelling gas since the start of her shift. Some workers had been moved to another part of the building, and others were sent briefly to a break room, but the warehouse had not been evacuated, according to accounts by Van Vorce and four others at work that night.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Robinson told Reveal that Amazon shut down the site for about an hour and a half while a maintenance team repaired the leak. But Van Vorce tells the dispatcher that management wouldn’t stop operations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““They’re trying to tell us we have to use our personal time if we want to leave,” she says in the 911 recording.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…picker at a fulfillment center in Phoenix until last year, said he and other workers would bring customers’ orders into the bathroom with them to scan midway through. “It sounds disgusting,” he acknowledged.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;““You have to hold your pee or not make your rate. Which one you want to do?” Shrum said. “I had to make my rate.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.revealnews.org/article/behind-the-smiles&quot;&gt;Reveal – Behind the Smiles: Amazon’s internal injury records expose the true toll of its relentless drive for speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2016/05/25/479509221/we-dont-know-how-many-workers-are-injured-at-slaughterhouses-heres-why&quot;&gt;NPR – We Don’t Know How Many Workers Are Injured At Slaughterhouses. Here’s Why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2018/jul/05/amputations-serious-injuries-us-meat-industry-plant&quot;&gt;The Guardian – Two amputations a week: the cost of working in a US meat plant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/capitalism/technology/2019/11/27/summary-behind-the-smiles.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/capitalism/technology/2019/11/27/summary-behind-the-smiles.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>capitalism</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Caring About Animals</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We tried to explain that we were interested in the prevention of suffering and misery; that we were opposed to arbitrary discrimination; that we thought it wrong to inflict needless suffering on another being, even if that being were not a member of our own species; and that we believed animals were ruthlessly and cruelly exploited by humans, and we wanted this changed. Otherwise, we said, we were not especially “interested in” animals.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Peter Singer, in Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a million things to care about in this world if we cared to care about – things that we know are systemically unfair, unjust or outright wrong. But if we cared about all of them to a point where we wanted to fix them or be a part of the solution, we’d go crazy. One way to maintain sanity is to accept that there are going to be things that are, and will be, out of our control and to learn to let go of some. That leaves us with the time and energy to think about what we value the most and work towards fixing them, in any way and capacity we can. Elon Musk might be a rare exception, or at least the most popular of them out there, who can not only think about but make a huge impact on solving a lot of the pressing issues in the world today. But to make my point, even he is not actively working towards fixing, let’s say, gun violence in the country. Most often, people care about a lot of things, but in varying degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I care a lot about autonomy, growth, health and fitness, to an extent where I spend a considerable amount of my time and energy learning/thinking about them, experimenting with them and optimizing them. I also care about the environment and animal welfare but I don’t proactively do a whole lot to cause any significant change. I keep myself educated about them and do the best I can without going above and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been brought up a vegetarian my entire life because of religious reasons, I neither questioned nor saw any inconsistencies in the stories we told ourselves about the choices we made about food. After reading about and watching the horrors of the dairy industry, I finally decided to give up dairy and egg and go vegan. It wasn’t easy in the beginning, but it happened at once when the evidence of the ill-effects of dairy, on my health and animals, was too clear and overwhelming to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve often felt out of place in vegan and animal welfare circles where people name the rescued animals, celebrate their birthdays, make them desserts and kiss them on their mouths. In that sense, I’m not an animal lover. I deeply care about animals, a bit more than I care about humans I’d say, and I can’t stand abuse or violence against them. I have cried just reading accounts of the treatment of animals for meat and fashion. I remember one time in fifth grade, right in front of my home, a few stray dogs had brutally injured a baby pig. The dogs neither killed nor ate its flesh. They injured it enough that it couldn’t move. If you’ve ever heard the noise of a pig squealing, you know it’s not a pleasant one. I cried my heart out and skipped school that day because I couldn’t step out of the door. It was a slow, painful death, for the pig and some tiny part of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also very sensitive to the blood of animals. I can’t see it. I’d probably faint if I saw an injured animal up close, bleeding. So, while I am hopelessly emotional about animals, I’m not mentally tough enough to help one, bloodily injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while reading &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;, a classic by Peter Singer, I realized that you don’t have to love animals to care about them and to believe in their moral rights and ethical treatment. You don’t have to have loved or even met a person in your life who has been a victim of some kind of discrimination, to ideologically believe that discrimination in any form - racial, sexual, intellectual - is immoral and wrong. So why expect that a person should love animals to believe in their welfare, autonomy, and rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d probably never own a pet, again. But that shouldn’t necessarily stop me from thinking or talking about animal welfare. It’s not an inconsistency, it’s irrelevant. Similarly, owning a pet doesn’t tell much about the extent to which a person cares about animals in general. The fundamental shift in thinking comes from a belief that non-human animals are not that different from us, and acknowledge, what’s now proved beyond doubt, that they experience pain and suffering very much like us. Once that’s established, other arguments start to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we get into a debate about this with others, it’s not so much about those animals as much as it’s about the moral values, prejudices, and biases we hold so dear. That’s why it reaches the level of intensity it does and gets the kind of emotional, sometimes irrational responses that it gets. It’s seeing the belief system collapse, or being shown the inconsistency and hypocrisy in what we think and do that gets to us. People often think that vegans and animal welfare activists ride on moral high ground. One argument to that is that people who sense that arrogance or superiority in others, might have a deep, latent insecurity about their own beliefs on a certain level. Another is that even if people who care about animals aren’t on higher ground, they are not on the lower ground either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you get into a discussion about this with someone with a different opinion, thinking of the following things might help to have a productive and sane debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think non-human animals are inferior to humans? If they do, on what grounds?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think animals experience pain and suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they believe torture and killing of some animals are different than others?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they know about the practices or treatment of animals being killed for meat and fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think that their preferences and likes matter more than the lives of animals?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From answers to these, you’ll know where they stand, and how likely they are to listen and understand your point of view. And if you can’t do a good job communicating your arguments, just ask them to read &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;. No matter what their argument is, I’m sure Peter Singer will have a better, more convincing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Animal-Liberation-Definitive-Classic-Movement/dp/0061711306&quot;&gt;Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/a&gt; (I’m currently reading this myself)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics/568/&quot;&gt;The Rights of Animals: A Very Short Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>animals</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time to Read</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
But I soon came to feel that teaching these sensitive young souls Latin and mathematics was cheating them of something far more essential — what they needed wasn’t dry information but hope, the kind that comes from being transported into a dream-world of possibility.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Helen Fagin, in The Velocity of Being: Letters to a Young Reader&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a chilly weekend morning. I’m standing by the side of a huge lake along with tens of other people, all rubbing their hands together to keep themselves warm. The water looks freezing and turbulent as if to throw us back on land if we were to venture out to take a dip. We’re all waiting for the organizers to blow a whistle to start the first leg of the triathlon. The shot’s fired and everybody starts jumping into the lake like a herd of lemmings out to commit suicide(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalplanet.com/wild-animals/do-lemmings-commit-suicide/&quot;&gt;it’s a myth, they apparently don’t actually do it&lt;/a&gt;). A punch here, a kick there and the unforgiving water. Bruised and exhausted, I somehow make it to the other end to see my bike ready to go. I take off my swim clothes, put on my biking outfit and I’m ready to go. The first half of the biking route is all uphill, and that’s where I plan to get ahead of everybody. My quads looking like wooden logs can hardly be contained in the biking shorts. I pedal as fast as I can on the uphill to pass people who beat me in water. At the top, I bring my back closer to the bike and take off in an aerodynamic position. Even with the sunglasses, tears from my eyes due to the headwinds fly backward as if they’re going to pierce through the rider behind. At the finish line, I apply the brakes, jump off the bike and let it ride further a few yards and crash on its own, like a bird with its neck chopped off. I change to running shorts and slowly ramp my speed in the last and final activity, the one that seems most familiar to me - running. Halfway through the race, somebody tells me that I have a shot at winning and by a huge margin. Tears out again but of happiness and joy this time. The last couple hundred feet I almost sprint as though my legs are green. I win the event and I see my parents at the finish line smiling. I sense a feeling of pride in their eyes, which makes me want to cry more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such vivid is the recollection of the triathlon that never happened. That’s right. While reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.richroll.com/finding-ultra/&quot;&gt;Finding Ultra&lt;/a&gt;, as I read the account of his feats in Hawaii, I pause for a few minutes and get lost in this imaginary race and I’m winning. I probably will never actually win a triathlon. But that imaginary race was still a very powerful motivator. Three years later, that and many such thoughts have fueled real and positive changes in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always felt at peace reading a book in a quiet place. I feel energized and excited to get to places where reading takes me. That feeling of getting inundated with ideas, freeing yourself from the constraints and conditioning of the real-world and letting your mind escape into a world of infinite potential and possibilities, asking yourself big questions and looking for answers within, is hugely inspiring and empowering. In that space and time, you’re neither in auto-pilot nor in the passenger seat. You’re the one in complete control. Making wrong moves there or taking a wrong turn doesn’t come with the judgments and repercussions of the real world. Instead, it comes with a deeper understanding of the consequences and rewards of your choices and helps you navigate the real world better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s much harder these days to get that lone space and time, harder than it needs to be. The eight or so hours that you spend at work is flooded with frequent and sometimes unnecessary meetings, direct or indirect conversations and breaks. You go home, spend some time with your partner, and eke out some time to read, write and workout. Not only do you have to carve time out for deep work, but you also have to make an extra effort to quell the mental chatter caused by entropy throughout the day. With the open floor plans in offices now, the passive conversations that you become part of just by being there feels like passive smoking to me. You end up bearing the brunt of something that you didn’t consciously choose to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it always is an ongoing battle to make time for things, the process of fighting for it also tells you something about what you value most, the things you consider are worth your time and that clarity eventually forces you to let go of the clutter - physical and mental, literal and metaphorical. So in a way, the fight for time is actually a fight for values, self-awareness, growth, a fight to shape and refine yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2018/12/18/a-velocity-of-being-helen-fagin/&quot;&gt;A 100-Year-Old Holocaust Survivor on How Books Save Lives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;Life is Short&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading</category>
        
        <category>time</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Ultra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long bike ride in July up in Colorado, I took it easy for a while and didn’t have any immediate goals to pursue. Had a couple of trips planned with my wife and some day hikes during the weekends, but that’s about it. I was feeling low for a few months after that and it took some time for me to realize that it was because of lack of something to look forward to. Not that I’m addicted to goals, but having a personal challenge and adventure to train towards keeps me physically and mentally healthy. I was turning 30 in October and a goal popped in my mind - to run at least 30 miles. The shortest official distance that meets the criterion is 50k, which is about 32 miles. The longest I had run so far was a 35k, which was in the year before, that’s about 22.5 miles. So 50k seemed like an ambitious, formidable, yet doable challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past the Labor Day weekend, so I had already lost the first week of September and since I wanted to do the race in the same month as my birthday, I had about 6-7 weeks to train. It seemed like a short time to go from 0 miles of running the whole year to 50k in a matter of a couple of weeks, so I had to start as soon as possible. I started the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is what the training looked like in numbers(Thanks to Strava!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re into long-distance running, you can tell that it looks like casual, weekday runs, nothing like training for an ultra at all. It’s true. Having made plans for the weekends ahead with my family and friends, weekdays were all I could get. I tried to squeeze at least two runs per week during lunch time, with each run somewhere between 5-8 miles. The longest run was about 10.5 mi and that was three weeks before the race. Sometimes due to lack of time, and other times because of my laziness, I didn’t go longer than that. And the runs were on flat roads, so I wasn’t getting any elevation training either. I had to first build up to the distance, before I could climb up. The race had about 5k ft of gain and descent. The thought of that in addition to pounding the legs for that long, scared me. The last two weeks I ventured out to the hilly blocks near my office in San Francisco and did some circuit runs to get my body(legs and glutes especially) used to uphill and downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---september&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - September&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-september.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar September&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---october&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - October&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-october.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar - October&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-log&quot;&gt;Run Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Log&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-distance&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-time&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-distance&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-time&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/the-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Race&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-reflections&quot;&gt;Notes and Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The race had a no-cup policy, so I carried a Nathan water bottle with me in hand. I think that works better for me than carrying a hydration pack, which rubs my back and gets the shirt all wet&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chafing is the worst. Even now, days after the race, my nipples hurt just thinking about it. I think right around mile 13, I took off my shirt and carried it pretty much from there up to a few yards before the finish line. I should take better care of it next time! Vaseline helps I think but I should look into some strap that hugs it tight and doesn’t cause friction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next time I sign up for something like this, I should do longer runs and on trails. That takes care of the boredom of long runs and also makes for a better training&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t get bored in trail runs. I had prepared a playlist of workout music and motivating podcasts to keep me going, especially in the end. But one, I didn’t need it and two, it ruins the fun of the race. When I slowed down in the last third of the race, I enjoyed the company of runners who were with me. Chatting with them, running with them helped me even speed up a little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GU is delicious and works well, I think. It’s really easy to eat on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gear&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newbalance.com/pd/Minimus-Trail-10/190325795818.html?ecid=ps_Google_pla_190325795818_1699205516&amp;amp;crtp=paidsearch&amp;amp;ncr=true&amp;amp;&amp;amp;CATARGETID=172000630002405320&amp;amp;CADevice=c&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAjwxt_tBRAXEiwAENY8hU7bNqAaUvQr4sk556T2MGHF4m5J3F30Jy7qvvDe9b_MznLsEbPS1BoCsSIQAvD_BwE&amp;amp;gclsrc=aw.ds#color=Black_with_Silver&amp;amp;size=8&amp;amp;width=2E&quot;&gt;New Balance Minimus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nathansports.com/collections/hydration/products/speedmax-plus-flask&quot;&gt;Nathan Handheld Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>running</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
