<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>out.of.desk</title>
    <description>My Online, Filtered Notepad</description>
    <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://outofdesk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 06:08:44 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 06:08:44 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Entrepreneurship and Dogs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2013, I was working in a startup with a team of about 10 engineers when one day we were all called for a team meeting. The founders were in the meeting so we knew it was something important. We were informed that the company was shutting down due to lack of funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had received admit a few days ago from one of the graduate schools I had applied to in the US and so I had a plan and two to three months of vacation ahead. One of the senior engineers in the team decided to work on his venture. Other people started looking for jobs, some founded their own companies too. He asked me if I would be willing to work with him to help build a Proof of Concept(POC). I had nothing to lose here. If it went well, I could always stay and potentially become a co-founder(yes, I passed that opportunity to go to graduate school!) or I could fly to the US in a few months and begin another new phase. It was a win-win for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he had savings to afford not having a job for up to a year and he knew a couple of people who could potentially invest in his idea. After we built the POC, we drove around to places on his motorbike, with our laptops and a “tea-and-biscuits” pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day after we parked the bike, he looked at a street dog sleeping on the road and told me something in Hindi(translated to English here): “We should have been born as those fucking street dogs. Didn’t have to worry so much about jobs or founding a company! We could just sleep all day.” That to me was hilarious. Something about his tone, his facial expression, the casual delivery and the humor about his struggle made it really funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think back on it and that episode seems profound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells something about human desire and imagination&lt;/em&gt; - How we always seek meaning in our lives, how we have this power to create something new, and even the audacity to imagine what a dog’s life must be like!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells about the attitude one can have even in difficult situations in life&lt;/em&gt; - The fact that he said that signals his frustration and anxiety, but also his attitude to make something funny out of it, rather than brooding over the situation and do nothing&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It tells something about the stories, sometimes false narratives we tell ourselves to get through life, our ability to see the “grass as always greener on the other side”&lt;/em&gt; - How we think others’ lives are easy, and that it would be so much better if we could trade their lives with ours. We only look at tiny slices of someone’s life and simplify them to make ourselves feel better.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;drive&lt;/strong&gt; that almost robs us of free will and calls the shots in our lives&lt;/em&gt; - His wife was pregnant at the time and was staying with her parents, so he had a couple of months to devote himself to something. He had enough money to take a vacation, but he chose (or was forced by his drive) to struggle, and to push himself to embark on a new and unknown journey.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He pivoted from the original idea that we had worked on but his company received a couple of rounds of funding and seems to be doing well now. So I guess he has moved on to define some new struggles and goals for himself to chase, as we always do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/struggle/2019/11/26/entrepreneurship-and-dogs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/struggle/2019/11/26/entrepreneurship-and-dogs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>struggle</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Caring About Animals</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We tried to explain that we were interested in the prevention of suffering and misery; that we were opposed to arbitrary discrimination; that we thought it wrong to inflict needless suffering on another being, even if that being were not a member of our own species; and that we believed animals were ruthlessly and cruelly exploited by humans, and we wanted this changed. Otherwise, we said, we were not especially “interested in” animals.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Peter Singer, in Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a million things to care about in this world if we cared to care about – things that we know are systematically unfair, unjust or outright wrong. But if we cared about all of them to a point where we wanted to fix them or be a part of the solution, we’d go crazy. One way to maintain sanity is to accept that there are going to be things that are and will be out of our control and to learn to let go of some. That leaves us with time and energy to think about what we value the most and work towards fixing them, in any way and capacity we can. Elon Musk might be a rare exception, or at least the most popular of them out there, who can not only think about but make a huge impact on solving a lot of the pressing issues in the world today. But to make my point, even he is not consciously and primarily working towards fixing let’s say the gun violence in America or the use of social media for disrupting elections and attempts to shake the institution of democracy. Most often, people care about a lot of things, but in varying degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I care a lot about my autonomy and growth, health and fitness, to an extent where I spend a considerable amount of my time and energy learning about them, experimenting with them and optimizing them. I also care about the environment and animal welfare but to a point where I don’t proactively do a whole lot to cause any actual change, but I keep myself constantly educating about them and do the best I can without going above and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been brought up a vegetarian my entire life because of religious beliefs, I neither questioned nor observed any inconsistencies in the foods we consumed and the stories we told ourselves about them. I always cared about animals and after reading about and watching the horrors of the dairy industry, I finally decided to give up dairy and egg and go vegan. It wasn’t easy in the beginning, but it happened at once when the evidence of the ill-effects of dairy, on my health and animals, was too clear and overwhelming to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve often felt out of place in vegan and animal welfare circles where people name the rescued animals, celebrate their birthdays, make them desserts and kiss them on their mouths. In that sense, I’m not an animal lover. I deeply care about animals, a bit more than I care about humans I’d say, and I can’t stand abuse or violence against them. I have cried just reading accounts of the treatment of animals for meat and fashion. I remember one time in fifth grade, right in front of my home, a few stray dogs had brutally injured a baby pig. The dogs neither killed nor ate its flesh. They injured it enough that it couldn’t move. If you’ve ever heard the noise of a pig squealing, you know it’s not a pleasant one. I cried my heart out and skipped school that day because I couldn’t step out of the door. It was a slow, painful death, for the pig and some tiny part of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also very sensitive to the blood of animals. I can’t see it. I’d probably faint if I saw an injured animal up close, bleeding. So, while I am hopelessly emotional about animals, I’m not mentally tough enough to help one, bloodily injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while reading &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;, a classic by Peter Singer, I realized that you don’t have to love animals to care about them and to believe in their moral rights and ethical treatment. You don’t have to have loved or even met a person in your life who has been a victim of some kind of discrimination, to ideologically believe that discrimination in any form - racial, sexual, intellectual - is immoral and wrong. So why expect that a person should love animals to believe in their welfare, autonomy, and rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d probably never own a pet, again. But that shouldn’t necessarily stop me from thinking or talking about animal welfare. It’s not an inconsistency, it’s irrelevant. Similarly, owning a pet doesn’t tell much about the extent to which a person cares about animals in general. The fundamental shift in thinking comes from a belief that non-human animals are not that different from us, and acknowledge, what’s now proved beyond doubt, that they experience pain and suffering very much like us. Once that’s established, other arguments start to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we get into a debate about this with others, it’s not so much about those animals as much as it’s about the moral values, prejudices, and biases we hold so dear. That’s why it reaches the level of intensity it does and gets the kind of emotional, sometimes irrational responses that it gets. It’s seeing the belief system collapse, or being shown the inconsistency and hypocrisy in what we think and do that gets to us. People often think that vegans and animal welfare activists ride on moral high ground. One argument to that is that people who sense that arrogance or superiority in others, might have a deep, latent insecurity about their own beliefs on a certain level. Another is that even if people who care about animals aren’t on higher ground, they are not on the lower ground either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you get into a discussion about this with someone with a different opinion, thinking of the following things might help to have a productive and sane debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think non-human animals are inferior to humans? If they do, on what grounds?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think animals experience pain and suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they believe torture and killing of some animals are different than others?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they know about the practices or treatment of animals being killed for meat and fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they think that their preferences and likes matter more than the lives of animals?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From answers to these, you’ll know where they stand, and how likely they are to listen and understand your point of view. And if you can’t do a good job communicating your arguments, just ask them to read &lt;em&gt;Animal Liberation&lt;/em&gt;. No matter what their argument is, I’m sure Peter Singer will have a better, more convincing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Animal-Liberation-Definitive-Classic-Movement/dp/0061711306&quot;&gt;Animal Liberation: A New Ethics for Our Treatment of Animals&lt;/a&gt; (I’m currently reading this myself)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics/568/&quot;&gt;The Rights of Animals: A Very Short Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/animals/2019/11/05/caring-about-animals.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>animals</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Time to Read</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
But I soon came to feel that teaching these sensitive young souls Latin and mathematics was cheating them of something far more essential — what they needed wasn’t dry information but hope, the kind that comes from being transported into a dream-world of possibility.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Helen Fagin, in The Velocity of Being: Letters to a Young Reader&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a chilly weekend morning. I’m standing by the side of a huge lake along with tens of other people, all rubbing their hands together to keep themselves warm. The water looks freezing and turbulent as if to throw us back on land if we were to venture out to take a dip. We’re all waiting for the organizers to blow a whistle to start the first leg of the triathlon. The shot’s fired and everybody starts jumping into the lake like a herd of lemmings out to commit suicide(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalplanet.com/wild-animals/do-lemmings-commit-suicide/&quot;&gt;it’s a myth, they apparently don’t actually do it&lt;/a&gt;). A punch here, a kick there and the unforgiving water. Bruised and exhausted, I somehow make it to the other end to see my bike ready to go. I take off my swim clothes, put on my biking outfit and I’m ready to go. The first half of the biking route is all uphill, and that’s where I plan to get ahead of everybody. My quads looking like wooden logs can hardly be contained in the biking shorts. I pedal as fast as I can on the uphill to pass people who beat me in water. At the top, I bring my back closer to the bike and take off in an aerodynamic position. Even with the sunglasses, tears from my eyes due to the headwinds fly backward as if they’re going to pierce through the rider behind. At the finish line, I apply the brakes, jump off the bike and let it ride further a few yards and crash on its own, like a bird with its neck chopped off. I change to running shorts and slowly ramp my speed in the last and final activity, the one that seems most familiar to me - running. Halfway through the race, somebody tells me that I have a shot at winning and by a huge margin. Tears out again but of happiness and joy this time. The last couple hundred feet I almost sprint as though my legs are green. I win the event and I see my parents at the finish line smiling. I sense a feeling of pride in their eyes, which makes me want to cry more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such vivid is the recollection of the triathlon that never happened. That’s right. While reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.richroll.com/finding-ultra/&quot;&gt;Finding Ultra&lt;/a&gt;, as I read the account of his feats in Hawaii, I pause for a few minutes and get lost in this imaginary race and I’m winning. I probably will never actually win a triathlon. But that imaginary race was still a very powerful motivator. Three years later, that and many such thoughts have fueled real and positive changes in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always felt at peace reading a book in a quiet place. I feel energized and excited to get to places where reading takes me. That feeling of getting inundated with ideas, freeing yourself from the constraints and conditioning of the real-world and letting your mind escape into a world of infinite potential and possibilities, asking yourself big questions and looking for answers within, is hugely inspiring and empowering. In that space and time, you’re neither in auto-pilot nor in the passenger seat. You’re the one in complete control. Making wrong moves there or taking a wrong turn doesn’t come with the judgments and repercussions of the real world. Instead, it comes with a deeper understanding of the consequences and rewards of your choices and helps you navigate the real world better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s much harder these days to get that lone space and time, harder than it needs to be. The eight or so hours that you spend at work is flooded with frequent and sometimes unnecessary meetings, direct or indirect conversations and breaks. You go home, spend some time with your partner, and eke out some time to read, write and workout. Not only do you have to carve time out for deep work, but you also have to make an extra effort to quell the mental chatter caused by entropy throughout the day. With the open floor plans in offices now, the passive conversations that you become part of just by being there feels like passive smoking to me. You end up bearing the brunt of something that you didn’t consciously choose to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it always is an ongoing battle to make time for things, the process of fighting for it also tells you something about what you value most, the things you consider are worth your time and that clarity eventually forces you to let go of the clutter - physical and mental, literal and metaphorical. So in a way, the fight for time is actually a fight for values, self-awareness, growth, a fight to shape and refine yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2018/12/18/a-velocity-of-being-helen-fagin/&quot;&gt;A 100-Year-Old Holocaust Survivor on How Books Save Lives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;Life is Short&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/time/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading</category>
        
        <category>time</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Ultra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long bike ride in July up in Colorado, I took it easy for a while and didn’t have any immediate goals to pursue. Had a couple of trips planned with my wife and some day hikes
during the weekends, but that’s about it. I was turning 30 in October and a random goal popped in my mind - to run at least 30 miles. The shortest official distance
that meets the criterion is 50k, which is about 32 miles. The longest I had run so far was a 35k the year before, which is about 22.5 miles. So it looked like an ambitious, formidable, yet doable challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past the Labor Day weekend, so I had already lost the first week of September and since I wanted to do the race in the same month as my birthday, I had about 6-7 weeks to train. It seemed like a short time to go from 0 miles of running the whole year to 50k in a stretch, so I had to start as soon as possible. I started the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the training looked like in numbers. If you’re into long-distance running, you can tell that it looks like casual, weekday runs, nothing like training for an ultra at all. It’s true. Having made plans for the weekends ahead with my family and friends, weekdays were all I could get. Tried to squeeze at least two runs per week, mostly somewhere between 5-8 miles during lunch. The longest run was about 10.5 mi and that was three weeks before the race. Sometimes due to lack of time, and sometimes because of my own laziness, I
didn’t go longer than that. And those long runs were on flat roads, so I wasn’t getting any elevation training either. The race had about 5k ft of gain and descent. The thought of that in addition to pounding the legs for that long, scared me. The last two weeks I ventured out to hilly blocks in the city around my workplace and did some circuit runs to get my body(legs and glutes especially) used to uphills and downhills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---september&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - September&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-september.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar September&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---october&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - October&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-october.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar - October&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-log&quot;&gt;Run Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Log&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-distance&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-time&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-distance&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-time&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/the-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Race&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-reflections&quot;&gt;Notes and Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The race had a no-cup policy, so I carried a Nathan water bottle with me in hand. I think that works better for me than carrying a hydration pack, which rubs my back and gets the shirt all wet&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chafing is the worst. Even now, days after the race, my nipples hurt just thinking about it. I think right around mile 13, I took off my shirt and carried it pretty much from there up to a few yards before the finish line. I should take better care of it next time! Vaseline helps I think but I should look into some strap that hugs it tight and doesn’t cause friction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next time I sign up for something like this, I should do longer runs and on trails. That takes care of the boredom of long runs and also makes for a better training&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t get bored in trail runs. I had prepared a playlist of workout music and motivating podcasts to keep me going, especially in the end. But one, I didn’t need it and two, it ruins the fun of the race. When I slowed down in the last third of the race, I enjoyed the company of runners who were with me. Chatting with them, running with them helped me even speed up a little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GU is delicious and works well, I think. It’s really easy to eat on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gear&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newbalance.com/pd/Minimus-Trail-10/190325795818.html?ecid=ps_Google_pla_190325795818_1699205516&amp;amp;crtp=paidsearch&amp;amp;ncr=true&amp;amp;&amp;amp;CATARGETID=172000630002405320&amp;amp;CADevice=c&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAjwxt_tBRAXEiwAENY8hU7bNqAaUvQr4sk556T2MGHF4m5J3F30Jy7qvvDe9b_MznLsEbPS1BoCsSIQAvD_BwE&amp;amp;gclsrc=aw.ds#color=Black_with_Silver&amp;amp;size=8&amp;amp;width=2E&quot;&gt;New Balance Minimus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nathansports.com/collections/hydration/products/speedmax-plus-flask&quot;&gt;Nathan Handheld Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed the post, feel free to share it on social media. If you have any questions or comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/running/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>running</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
