<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>out.of.desk</title>
    <description>My Public Experiments in Writing</description>
    <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://outofdesk.github.io/sitemap.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 17:12:55 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 17:12:55 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brooks' Law as a Special Case of Amdahl's Law</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;brooks-law&quot;&gt;Brooks’ Law&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Wikipedia: &lt;em&gt;“Brooks’ law is an observation about software project management according to which “adding manpower to a late software project makes it later”&lt;/em&gt;. This was put forth by Fred Brooks in his classic book “The Mythical Man Month”, in 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons as explained by Brooks are three-fold, which I thik can be reduced to the following two, after merging last two of the original three together&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any time spent in getting the newer members productive, is time stolen from the time until the deadline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inherent lack of divisibility – The less divisible the tasks are, the more the time spent in managing their dependencies and communication. Again, any time not directly spent in working towards the delivery is time stolen from the time until the deadline, at least in the short-term. The famous example captures the essence of this quite aptly: “While one woman can deliver a baby in nine months, nine women can’t deliver a baby in one month”. Since the “work”, in the example, is completely indivisible, the benefit of adding more manpower, or womanpower in this case, yields zero benefit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amdahls-law&quot;&gt;Amdahl’s Law&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amdahl’s law, presented by Gene Amdahl in 1967, states that “the overall performance improvement gained by optimizing a single part of a system is limited by the fraction of time that the improved part is actually used”. It is often used in parallel computing to predict the improvement in performance achieved by using multiple processors. An example of this is that if a task is 10% non-parallelizable, then any benefit of adding more processors only applies for the rest of the 90% of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the language used to describe them and the realms they are applied in are different, the idea is the same. In fact, Amdahl’s law is a general case of Brooks’ law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;amdahls-law-in-project-management&quot;&gt;Amdahl’s Law in Project Management&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deadline is the time at which you’re expected to be completed with the project. Let’s say the deadline is time D. If the time at which you add more resources is time T, then you’d get the most benefit out of adding more people to a project if the period they are actually contributing directly towards the release is D-T, i.e. all the rest of the time until the deadline. But since a non-trivial amount of time is lost in bringing them up to speed, your team ends up spending until, let’s say, time X. Hence the fraction of time the additional resources(improved part) are actually used is limited to &lt;em&gt;D-T-X&lt;/em&gt; at most, assuming no further dependencies and communication. If the project is already running behind schedule, it means that you just stole precious time, most likely leading to missing the deadline. The overall benefit is hence limited by the indivisibility of tasks in some parts of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/management/2022/03/29/brooks-law-amdahls-law.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/management/2022/03/29/brooks-law-amdahls-law.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>management</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adopting and Embracing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;All the companies I’ve been a part of, practice Agile methodologies for software development. Some of them considered lack of planning, processes, and practices as part of being agile because we were changing course all the time. A majority of the rest of them followed it by the book, focusing on the rituals, the jargon and the expected outcomes. They had Sprint planning, retrospectives, daily stand-ups, backlog grooming, and story point estimation. But it seemed dry for the most part. Engineers hated the tools, and the rituals. They felt like they were being dragged to meetings and being asked to talk when they would rather be building stuff that was actually useful. For all the shiny promises of Agile, it didn’t &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; so great, it didn’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; so great. Things got done still – we shipped features, we built systems, we made money – some on time, some not. But mere completion is a low bar to measure the success of teams and organizations. The journey of Agile felt like traveling in a car that reached its destination but left all the passengers with a nauseating feeling. We did things the right way and checked all the boxes. The lights, the engine, the brakes, the acceleration, the fuel – everything was fine. But something still &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; missing. It was hard to point out what was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens in other aspects of life too, when we do things not because of its inherent value, but from the influence of external forces – peer pressure, fear of missing out, external validation, culture, trends and so on. We travel to distant and exotic places over the weekends, even if we don’t feel like it, only to go back home exhausted, depleted and discontent. Traveling is what people do when they get a break from work, right? We follow and adopt trending diets or fitness routines, even when our body or mind rejects the idea. We aim to earn more money, regardless of how much we have, because society attributes it to success. The pattern is this: we focus more on the outcomes than the path taken, more on the ends than the means. And when we do that, no matter how exciting or promising the outcome is, deep down we still yearn to fill the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I follow a plant-based diet. People in my social circle who don’t, ask me how hard it is to follow a diet like that. They think that I’m disciplined and good at self-control. There could be a little bit of that, but that’s not what keeps me going. If I were battling with myself every time I saw a dessert, or any of the rich, creamy dishes that Indian cuisine has to offer, I’d have given up the vegan diet long ago. What keeps me at it is the reason I chose to make the switch in the first place. For me, it is primarily about reducing harm to animals. My commitment to that cause is unwavering. And I don’t say that with the slightest sense of arrogance. I’ve always been sensitive and empathetic towards other beings, since childhood. I was wired that way, so I’ve no reason to be riding the moral high ground. &lt;em&gt;Why I adopted&lt;/em&gt; a plant-based diet has been the reason for &lt;em&gt;why it has stuck&lt;/em&gt; long-term. So, how I do it almost becomes moot. I like the idea of a life that minimizes harm to others, and so I find ways to do it. It’s embracing a life that minimizes suffering to other beings, rather than the idea of adopting a plant-based life, that has made the journey more fulfilling, while producing the desired outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While people have different reasons for their choices, none wrong in itself, some make it easier for you to be at peace with the choices. You can adopt something to be good at it – you can lose weight without enjoying physical exercise, you can excel at your job without liking it. Adopting something is to value the desired outcome. Embracing it is to love the process. It is to change your mindset. Ultra-runners and other endurance athletes often talk about how they embrace the struggle and the suffering. It doesn’t make the journey any easier, but it does make it easier to not give up, to keep going, to endure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m reading about Agile methodologies, I’m fascinated by the why behind the values and principles stated. Learning about the reasons behind why a group of experts in the software industry decided to meet to solve certain problems, and the reasons for why they chose the values and principles they did, helps me understand the mindset they had. It helps me embrace the idea, rather than merely adopt the outcome. It reinforces the belief that the hardest problems in building software systems aren’t technological. Being Agile is a commitment, not unlike being in a relationship. You don’t always stick to the rules, but you always try to make it work, not because you have to, but because you want to. It starts with the mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/mindset/musings/2022/03/08/adopting-and-embracing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/mindset/musings/2022/03/08/adopting-and-embracing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mindset</category>
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I Tried</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“I Tried”&lt;/strong&gt; – That’s what I think my tombstone should say. I’ll most likely not have a tombstone, of course. My body will be burned in the funeral pyre, according to the Hindu traditions, so my soul can rest in peace. But if I had one, I’d like it to say that. The statement accurately captures how I live, or at that point, how I’ll have lived. I &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to do things to the best of my ability and I &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to get better, and not only with the things I want to be good at, but also with those that others expect me to do. I care a lot more about what people think than I like to admit. It bothers me sometimes, how much I care about what other people think and want. The conflict between my needs and others’ cripples me at times even. But that quality runs deep. An interplay of nature and nurture has deeply ingrained the value of collective good in me, that makes me guilty of pursuing things that are born purely out of self-interest. And so while I &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to strike a balance, I also &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to make peace with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the different roles I play – a husband, a son, a brother, a friend, an engineer, a colleague, a runner, a reader, a learner, a writer – and yes, I think of them as roles that I play, I &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to perform well. Whether I’m successful in my attempts is a different matter, and sometimes beyond my control, what is though, is &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt;. And so I do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This constant need to get better is also a source of pain sometimes, especially when working with people who I find complacent. I realize that a perfectionist attitude can be a recipe for misery, and I’m guilty of that, of &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to be perfect. Acknowledging that you have a perfectionist attitude seems like self-flattery, but it’s nothing to be proud of, and it doesn’t tell much about how good you are. It merely indicates that you are dissatisfied more often than not. It sounds like a good thing because it has the word “perfect” in it, but it robs you of the little successes you have while &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to get better. Nothing seems good enough. So I’m also &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to learn how not to aim for perfection, or as they say, how to become a friend of the good rather than the perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Children are good at &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt;. Their curious minds and lack of fear make for a good combination in helping them &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; without restraints. Not only are they naturally good at it, they are expected to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; and fail. We gradually become more set in our ways as we grow old. While it’s partly due to the lessened curiosity, the slowing of neuroplasticity, we blame the making of our brain more than it deserves. Research has found evidence of incredible neuroplasticity even in adulthood given the right circumstances. It’s largely the fear of failure that holds us back. It’s more psychological than it is anatomical. There’s a negative connotation to &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt;. You are expected to have tried until a certain age and then know enough to not have to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; again. And so exercising the mind stops much before we stop exercising the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trying&lt;/em&gt; is not assertive enough, not confident enough; it isn’t good enough. Heck, even the tools that help improve your English writing suggest not to hedge, when you use such words. Culturally, the focus is more on the outcome than the means, and so &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; is pushed behind the curtains, while victories and failures take the center stage. That’s not to say that mere &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; should be rewarded, no. That could inadvertently encourage pretense. But it could use a little good publicity. &lt;em&gt;Trying&lt;/em&gt; is good and it needs to be treated as such. It’s challenging but rewarding in the end. You learn things that you don’t expect. Society is better off when individuals &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; rather than see it as pointless. &lt;em&gt;Trying&lt;/em&gt; means to not lose hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; is hard! Yes, it is. As they say, no good things in life come easy. There’s always a chance we might get lucky, but we will have a better chance of succeeding if we try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; takes time! Yes, it does, but what doesn’t? Not &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; also takes time! It’s just spent elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few episodes in the series Big Bang Theory where Sheldon corrects people that he didn’t merely &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to accomplish scientific feats in childhood, he succeeded at them. Being successful at something brings with it a sense of smugness that clouds our view of the humble beginnings of &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt;. That’s especially true of people who haven’t failed at things. It’s hard to appreciate the beauty of &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt;, if all you’ve had are wins at the first attempt. I’ve always admired people who genuinely &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to get better, be better. It’s the lack of willingness to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt;, or feigning to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; that I find repulsive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That happens a lot with the act of listening. People often don’t even &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt;. They merely wait for others to finish so they can speak. That’s probably one of the causes of the majority of arguments and fights – people not &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to listen to others. I’m guilty of it myself and I’m sure most people are. It’s hard to know it at the time you’re doing it, but reflecting on your actions and choices help identify it after the fact. It also helps you rethink, reassess and &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; other things, in other ways. In this messy, complex and beautiful world of infinite choices, that’s all we can do – &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think that it’s an attempt to make &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; look good, but it might just as well be something that I’m &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to convince myself of, a consolation I’m giving myself for not succeeding at the things I &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt;, or a story I’m telling myself to look past my failures. I can’t know for sure but I can hope it is what I think it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2022/02/04/i-tried.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2022/02/04/i-tried.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maturing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Merriam Webster dictionary defines a toy as something that a child plays with. That’s the context in which the word is most used. But it also defines it as something, such as a preoccupation, that’s paltry or trifling. Kids obviously don’t think of toys as trivial; it’s us, the adults, who think they are. We also think that we give up toys as we grow up, suggesting that what we preoccupy ourselves with is somehow more important and serious. But that’s hardly true. We merely start playing more refined games, with more sophisticated toys. Money, ego, gadgets, fancy cars and other such material possessions are all toys in some sense. Our misplaced priorities make them far more important in our lives than they deserve to be. One thing that’s common between kids and adults is that we seldom think about the need, or utility, of toys. Kids, up to a certain age, can’t reason, and adults often don’t. Such desires come from a more primitive part of the brain. They are the answers that are handed to us down by somebody but to questions that we have long lost. I had never given much thought to what it means to be mature. But as I write this, it seems to me that an important part of maturing is one’s ability to reason about their emotions, behavior, and choices. That’s why we call people child-like, or immature, when they act like free spirits, doing things in a carefree way. What we mean when we say that is that they don’t think through things and that their choices don’t seem rational. While it’s good to be like that at times, in some form and fashion, it has its problems too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of software, tools, frameworks, and patterns are toys. Freshly minted engineers, like kids, are enamored by the world of infinite choices. They focus more on exploring what’s available than on their utility. Just as a child’s brain develops from being exposed to ideas, an engineer’s mind sharpens from being exposed to the possibilities of technology. Part of evolving as an engineer is to start seeing technology as a means to solve real-world problems rather than as an end in itself. By that definition, I feel like Silicon Valley has lost its way. Companies are increasingly coming up with solutions to problems of their own conception, and then trying to convince people about the existence of them. The power of technology and the maturity of people holding the power are heading in opposite directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first job after college I worked as a frontend engineer and was tasked with building web and mobile apps. Building user interfaces was not what I had in mind when I thought about putting my knowledge and skills in Computer Science into use. But as I grew more familiar with it, I came to love it more. I liked being able to see the product I was building, as I was building it, and to be able to see it from the lens of the customer. The field was also more dynamic than the backend ecosystem at the time. New frameworks and tools sprung up every day and like a kid who’s handed new toys, I enjoyed tinkering with them. Anything that was deemed cool drew my attention. My age and experience working in technology matched the age and maturity of the domain of frontend engineering itself. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gardeviance.org/2013/01/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; says about the lifecycle of ecosystems, frontend engineering was accelerating in the phase of innovation while the backend ecosystem was thriving in the phase of commoditization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years later, I went to graduate school, to study more of what I hadn’t used in my job. After school I got back into frontend engineering, to do more of what I didn’t learn in grad school. I don’t say that with the slightest of regret or guilt. It has taught me things that I would have otherwise never learned, most important of all, empathy for designers and frontend engineers. The realm of frontend engineering was markedly different relative to what it had been two years ago. In the time I did my Master’s, MVC frameworks in the browser gave way to reactive, event-driven systems. After a few more years of building user experiences at scale, I finally felt exhausted by the constant need to catch up with the trends of the industry. I found myself spending more time debating about the tools and frameworks rather than the problems we could solve. Backend engineering, at least from my vantage point, seemed like a more reasonable, a more stable, place. So I switched my focus to backend engineering a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar change happened recently when engineering challenges started to hold less of my attention than the other critical aspects of the work we do – people, principles, and processes. I grew curious to explore the paths of management and leadership. To be an engineer is to focus on how to build good systems; to be a technologist is to also care about what and why we build systems using technology. Their value is not nearly as acknowledged by engineers, but it has been amazing to see how laying out the purpose and focusing on people, principles and processes organically lead to better engineering solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes of perspectives and desires perhaps say something about my maturing as an engineer, a technologist, and a human. While no one decision, or choice, makes you mature, it’s the ability to reflect and reevaluate, to be more aware of what drives you, that hints at your maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/technology/musings/2022/01/29/maturing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/technology/musings/2022/01/29/maturing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Book Notes: Cloud Native Patterns</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I read the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manning.com/books/cloud-native-patterns&quot;&gt;Cloud Native Patterns, by Cornelia Davis&lt;/a&gt;, I plan to use this space to document things I learn, read and think about along the way. As such, I expect this to be a constantly changing and evolving post, much like the cloud systems that the book talks about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-first before cloud-native&lt;/strong&gt; – Cloud-first is a good precursor to understanding what cloud-native means and what it has to offer. Although the way people define cloud-first strategy varies widely, it essentially is thinking of the cloud as the primary medium of running your software, as opposed to the older approach that tied all your systems to a set of servers with dedicated resources in a specific physical location that you owned or managed. Cloud, more than anything, is a layer of abstraction built to free the developers’ minds from the concerns of how to run systems and promote thinking about what to build. Hence moving to the cloud doesn’t necessarily mean taking your systems off-premises, but it’s a way of how you think(or rather, how much you don’t think) about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural Side-effects of moving to the cloud&lt;/strong&gt; – Think of taking care of your babies at home versus sending them to daycare. A natural and inevitable side-effect of sending your baby away for a few hours is that you lose some control. It’s neither good or bad, it just is. So while it relieves you of some duties and responsibilities, it also raises the stakes in other ways. Similarly, when you take your systems from your premises to the cloud, it means that you lose some control. But it doesn’t magically solve all your problems, it solves some, and throws other, newer problems at you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inherent characteristics of the cloud&lt;/strong&gt; – Going back to the daycare example, it’s a more dynamic place than your home. There are other actors at play – other babies, the care-givers, other babies’ parents, and the challenges of an unfamiliar setting. In other words, it’s a chaotic place. Things are not always predictable, and are bound to go wrong, in one way or the other. Because of the sheer number of unknowns, learning about all of them, let alone preventing all the problems is not an option. Cloud is exactly like that too. There are other systems at play, their dependencies, and the shared infrastructure, needless to say all that bound by the laws of Physics. It sounds scary at first, but accepting these truths enables us to think about how to build systems that function amidst the chaos, despite all the failings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So why go to the cloud&lt;/strong&gt; – If you lose control and visibility into our systems, why on Earth would you want to migrate? Because absolute control and perfection are delusional goals to build your life or business upon. And while you lose some control on how your systems work together, you gain control on what your systems does, or how they provide value to the customers. If you had all the time in the world, you would have taken care of your babies at home. Not that you don’t like them going out, but that you would like to be around them as much as you can. But time is finite, and society and its changing needs throw a lot at you to juggle. In order to do the best with your time, you prioritize things and delegate or outsource some responsibilities. As technology has come to dominate most people’s lives, the changing needs of society often translates to changing needs of software. As the demand of your business increases, you’re compelled to not only prioritize time, but the limited material resources you possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desirable characteristics of a successful business&lt;/strong&gt; – In order to serve the ever-changing needs of the society, certain characteristics naturally emerge that are desirable to run a successful business. Simply put, a business should provide the value promised to all its customers, anywhere and anytime, and evolve quickly to address their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All its customers&lt;/em&gt; – In the world of the Internet, your customers come from different backgrounds, cultures, ages, and gender, they use different devices, and operate under widely different constraints. So accessibility, multi-language and multi-device support now become first-class citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anywhere and anytime&lt;/em&gt; – When your customers are based in different geographical locations across continents, compliance to legal and other policies, and the ability to operate in different time-zones, essentially being available around the clock are of prime importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evolve quickly&lt;/em&gt; – Evolving quickly to serve such a diverse group of customers and a unique set of constraints means having shorter and accurate feedback cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-native&lt;/strong&gt; – is an umbrella term used to capture a set of ideas, principles, processes and tools, that aims to marry the inherent characteristics of the cloud with the desirable characteristics of today’s businesses in a seamless manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manning.com/books/cloud-native-patterns&quot;&gt;Cloud Native Patterns, by Cornelia Davis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/architecture/cloud-native/definition&quot;&gt;What is Cloud Native&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/technology/2022/01/22/cloud-native-patterns.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/technology/2022/01/22/cloud-native-patterns.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Run in Boston</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is about my musings on a run in Boston, not the Boston Marathon, but the kind of run that the majority of people do – to clear their mind, to get some fresh air, to escape the buzz of their busy lives, to listen to their body and mind, to improve their health and fitness, to escape from their problems, or find solutions to them, to exercise control over their life, to explore a place, to socialize. It was the kind where the body’s not constantly hurting and, mainly, where conscious thinking happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 6.30 AM, I took an Uber from the hotel I was staying at to go to Charles River Esplanade, a park near MIT, for an easy long run. The driver asked me if I was going for a run and started a conversation with me about running. The fact that the first person I met in the city started talking to me about running and marathons made me think about how common and deeply wired running must be in the city for it to become a part of the vernacular. After he dropped me off, I oriented myself by looking at Google maps and checking it against the streets and landmarks around me to see where I was and where I was supposed to be going. Although I saw a few runners on a nearby bridge, I didn’t know enough about the place and the people to trust or follow others’ leads. My mind, like Tom Vanderbilt says in his book Beginners, was alert, inquisitive, and cautiously skeptical. I was a beginner trying to navigate this new place on my own, both physically and mentally. After a few minutes of running toward the river and the bridge close by, I found myself on the trail that ran along the river. My mind then loosened up, going from a mode of figuring to a mode of exploring, from problem-solving to observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I knew how big the Boston Marathon is in running circles, I had never quite associated the city with running for some reason. It didn’t occur to me that Boston was where the Boston Marathon happened. What came to mind when I thought about Boston were MIT, Harvard, Boston Globe, the newspaper, and the movie Spotlight. The thought of going for a run occurred to me only the day before when I was sitting in the rear seat of the rental car that my brother was driving. We were returning to Boston from Maine, where we had spent the last few days experiencing the fall foliage. I had a few hours to kill the next day before we left for the airport back home. Given that others were exhausted from the trip and were looking forward to a warm shower and a good night’s sleep, I thought I could make the best use of it by getting up early and finishing my run before others woke up. Among the many benefits of early morning runs, one is that you get to do what you enjoy but also be present for the people you’re with. As far as they are concerned you never left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I started the run, from MIT to Harvard and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;structures-and-influences&quot;&gt;Structures and Influences&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every structure in and around the college campus was a distinct reminder of the imperial, Christian, and Caucasian history of the place. Their presence to this day, or rather the absence of anything that relates to the native tribes, hints at their hegemony. Streets, benches, and buildings with White names, the vestigial language of the feudal times that describe certain areas as a place for “commons”, the Christian influence on the architecture – all make it seem like the city still largely reflects the culture and beliefs of the time it was constructed in like it’s a snapshot, frozen in space, yet moving forward in time. I had always wondered why marginalized minorities fixated on the removal of historical remains that remind them of the oppressive times. I used to think of them as futile attempts at trying to change the immutable – the past. But it dawned on me that it’s not so much as rewriting the past as it is about selectively removing the traces of pain, to make space for communal healing. In that sense, it’s not very different from the methods we use to get past grief in our lives, like time spent in a bad relationship. We delete the photos, unfriend the person and throw away anything that reminds us of it/them every day, in order to move on. Although the methods we employ are the same, it’s relatively easier to move on from the individual past than the shared past. From that perspective, I see how it could be useful, even important, to remove the signs of the tragic past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing about structures: people build structures based on their own and the collective ideas, beliefs, and norms of their time, the structures outlive them thus capturing the essence of a certain time and of the people at the time, the structures then embody the past and shape the future. It’s as if the artifacts of a time were uploaded into a flash drive and then passed on to the next generation. The world we construct is the flash drive that gets passed on, the form and structures of the world we build are the contents of it. It’s hard to see it that way because the carrier and the contents are bigger than any one individual. Much like the workings of human memory which optimizes storage by retaining only a gist of the events in the past and recalls or reenacts it by filling the gaps, the thoughts and decisions of the past are captured and retained not in every brick of a structure, but as the structure itself. The structure is the gist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-dark-irony&quot;&gt;The Dark Irony&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s demographic, although changing, is largely white and that shows in the running groups out on the trails too. In a loop of about 8.5 miles, I saw only a handful of non-white people, and if you knew the number of runners you would stumble upon in Boston in a stretch that long, you’d know that that percentage is minuscule. The fact, then, that the Boston Marathon podium is dominated by Black runners year after year is a kind of dark irony of the whole system. It’s a slap in the face of not any individual entity, but of the manufactured myths of the superiority of race that are so blatantly and gracefully proved to be false time and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-myth-to-reality-from-feeling-to-reasoning&quot;&gt;From Myth to Reality; From Feeling to Reasoning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the run, I wondered how fascinating it was that an idea, a desire to run, that originated in the mind, became a reality in the physical world. Although forces outside our control have to converge for us to realize our dreams and desires, deliberate effort is what sets things in motion for them to happen. It makes me think about the kind of free will Daniel Dennet talks about, that he argues is the kind worth having, even if it’s theoretically an illusion. We don’t often care as much about how some thoughts occur to us as much as we do about the sense of agency we feel to make them happen when we want. Even if the theory of determinism about our realities was true, it doesn’t discount the fact that the kind of free will we think we possess is what brings a sense of fulfillment and meaning to our existence. This stress on physical reality, or more importantly, the rejection of psychological or subjective reality that the scientists openly and proudly partake in, the denial of the tools and frameworks that are only mythical in nature yet serve as a guideline for our lives is what strikes me as a setback introduced by the age of Enlightenment. The shift is not completely accidental either. It serves the purpose of the people who came up with the ideas. To feel you merely need to be alive, but to reason or debate, you need resources, both intellectual and physical, resources that, although seem free to acquire, can be denied to you, and the denial of which takes the power away from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;back-as-a-changed-person&quot;&gt;Back as a Changed Person&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the flight a few hours later to fly back home and started the grind of the job the next day, as a slightly different person, with a slightly different perspective on things. The change that happens after travel is seldom as transformational as the culture or the media wants us to believe. It often is more subtle than that, so tiny or obscure sometimes that it takes reflection to bring them to the surface of consciousness. It’s that unquantifiable yet real change that happens that we travel for, or rather we should travel for, that we started to travel for. The real value of travel is neither in satiating the craving for novelty that the consumerist culture wants us to have, nor in telling other people about the adventure to seek validation, but it’s in the places we get to in our mind from the change in the physical landscape, it’s in the food it feeds our senses, it’s in the change that happens within us. I have often asked myself and failed to answer why it’s bad to be engaged in social media when you’re out in nature. It’s like going to a train station wanting to experience a train ride, but having come back being content merely with the sight of the train. There’s nothing right or wrong about that, but it’s the missed opportunities and experiences that we could have had but didn’t, and worse yet, that we did want to have but didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1895587/&quot;&gt;Spotlight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/06/theres-no-such-thing-as-free-will/480750/&quot;&gt;There’s no such thing as free will – The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/news/2021/apr/27/the-clockwork-universe-is-free-will-an-illusion&quot;&gt;The clockwork universe: is free will an illusion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08DFRFH6X&quot;&gt;Beginners: The Joy and Transformative Power of Lifelong Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/reflections/2021/11/07/run-in-boston.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/reflections/2021/11/07/run-in-boston.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Grand Canyon R2R2R</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At around 5.30 pm on Friday, Apr 23, 2021, my friend and I hopped in the shuttle bus that carried us from the visitor center to South Kaibab trailhead in Grand Canyon National Park. We had just arrived in the area, set up our tents at Mather Campground, and drove to the visitor center. I could feel butterflies in my gut because of the excitement, fear, and nervousness I was going through, all at the same time, for what we were about to embark on. It’s a familiar feeling, an old friend. It’s the same feeling I get before a public presentation or some kind of a test. It’s also something I feel before every adventure. It indicates that whatever I’m about to do is important enough to make me want to do it regardless of the consequences. There’s a certain element of fear involved too, of failure, because of the high stakes that I attach to such things in my mind. It also usually means that it’s a little out of the comfort zone, just enough to create uncertainty and doubt about the outcome and my capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were attempting a hike called the R2R2R, short for Rim-to-Rim-to-Rim, in a day. It involves starting at one rim(North or South) of the canyon, hiking to the other, and then back again. Considered to be one of the most iconic and difficult hikes in North America, it’s about 45 mi long, with 14k feet of elevation gain and loss, and the trail, although well maintained, is rocky. It wasn’t technically a run, more like an ultra-hike. Some people go from almost no running to running ultra-marathons in a matter of months, or take the leap from road running to trail running and crush it. Not me. I take small, cautious, and incremental steps. It has taken me two years of hiking, running, and mental strengthening to get to running a 50k(32mi). In other words, I’m fairly slow, not merely on the trail, but also in taking leaps of faith. I found out fairly quickly that speed isn’t my strong suit and that I enjoy the solitude during a run more than anything. So I naturally gravitated towards trail running. I also don’t do well in a competitive setting. Material or external goals and pressures don’t motivate me. I like the idea of a personal challenge without the fuss of competition. That’s another reason why trail running suits me better. After having had one 50k under my belt from two years ago, I thought that hiking 45mi in a day probably wasn’t going to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sign on one of the windows of the bus said, “Many hikers think they are strong and attempt hikes beyond their capabilities. Don’t be one of them. Know your limits” and a whistle started to go off in my mind. It’s not like I need any real reason to go into self-doubt - my mind is happy to create reasons of its own - so this sign, to put it mildly, didn’t help calm me at that moment. Ever since I read the novel “The Alchemist’’, by Paulo Coelho, I’ve been a believer in signals of the Universe, and that it’s up to us to identify and unpack them. It’s a superstitious belief, I know, but it keeps me curious and attuned to the opportunities and warnings around me. It’s also an interesting idea because what you make of those signals tells more about your inner state than about the Universe. I took the sign on the bus as a warning for me to back off before I did something stupid. I felt like I was the ignorant hiker that it was referring to. Brain, with all its mysteriousness and capabilities, is also naive and stupid at times. It can’t always tell the difference between what’s real and what’s not. I wondered if it knew the difference between what I did a few years ago and what I was capable of in the present. I questioned if I knew myself well enough or if I was stuck in the stories from the past. As I was thinking about it, the bus dropped us at the trailhead and it was time to get off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the trailhead, I saw a few people massaging their legs, beaten but at the same time elated and mildly proud. I knew that they had run the R2R2R trail - they were ultra-runners! I asked one of the guys how long it took him to do that and he said ten hours. We had given ourselves twenty-four hours. If those runners could do it in less than half that time, I thought, our goal wasn’t that too hard after all. What those runners had done made our oh-so-ambitious goal look pale in comparison. Talking to them helped because it put me in the right mindset. I felt a little more confident, more optimistic and I conveniently forgot the signal of the Universe that I was pondering a few minutes ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watched people at the trailhead, I thought that this was a gateway to a world of possibilities. Like in life, we all started at the same place, but ended up on different paths, choosing different adventures depending on our needs, desires, experiences, and capabilities. Some were just happy to be there. They didn’t need anything more from it. They saw the canyons, took pictures, and enjoyed the company of their friends and family. A majority of the visitors ventured a little further to a vista point, aptly called the “Ooh Aah Point”, which was a mile into the trail. The more adventurous ones hiked down to the river, at the bottom of the canyon, and hiked back. Some stayed there overnight, camping and enjoying the canyons and the river for a little longer.  The more capable ones hiked to the other rim, camped there, and hiked back the next day, or extended the trip to more than two days. People who were in it for the challenge of it more than anything else, hiked to the other rim and back in one stretch, either running, walking, or crawling. I was the kind who’d dream of running, start walking and end up crawling. I’m not sure what that makes me – adventurous, brave, strong, and capable, or merely a wannabe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started the hike at 06.00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had broken the hike into six sections to have a mental map of how much was done, or more importantly, of how much wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;13&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:16px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 19% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;50px&quot; height=&quot;50px&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 60 60&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; xmlns=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;none&quot; stroke-width=&quot;1&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot;&gt;&lt;g transform=&quot;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&quot; fill=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding-top: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&quot;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 12.5% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: auto;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/COJotaVnuhM/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Gaurav Ramesh | 🌿🏃🚴⛺📷 (@out.of.desk)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-1-the-trailhead-to-phantom-ranch&quot;&gt;Section 1. The Trailhead to Phantom Ranch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comprises the first seven miles of the hike, all downhill, where you lose about 5k ft in elevation until you get to the bottom of the canyon. Despite constituting a third of the entire distance, in terms of the effort and energy needed, it’s more like a tenth. The Colorado River at the bottom, depending on the time of the year, can be spectacular scenery. We hiked at the end of April when the fresh snow melted by the early summer sun brought a loud gush of water. It was very tempting to run this section and be done as fast as I could, but I resisted giving in to that because the hike was long and hard and I wanted to save every bit of energy for the hike back and up. This was similar to the tug of war that plays in our mind every day between instant gratification and the long-term benefits of not succumbing to its pull. The former is natural and easier to seek, but it’s the hard things that are often worth doing. Running downhill is tough on the knees too, so it was better to walk fast than run, to reduce stress on the joints. Hiking poles were helpful and acted as the extra support, the support that we lost sometime millions of years ago when our ancestors learned to stand upright on two limbs. There was drinking water at the end of the section, so I had started merely with two bottles of water and sipped away as much as I wanted. It was already starting to get dark towards the end, but the full moon brought enough light to the floor of the canyon that I didn’t require headlamps. The trail was bumpy, so it might not have been wise to walk partially blindly in the moonlight, but since I didn’t fall or trip, in retrospect, it now seems like a good idea to have put my visual senses and attention to use to navigate. It was certainly a unique experience. With more reliance on our evolutionary making than on technology, I felt closer to our simpler, pre-modern ancestors, like I was living how we are supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-2-phantom-ranch-to-manzanita&quot;&gt;Section 2. Phantom Ranch to Manzanita&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is nine miles of almost flat trails, where you gain about 2.5k to 3k ft in elevation, and is the most comfortable section of the hike, at least for the legs. It’s your best chance to make up for time lost in the climbs. There was no drinking water here, but you’d be walking right along the river, so you could always filter from it if you were dying of dehydration. This section could be further divided into two, 7.5 mi to Cottonwood campground and 1.5 mi to Manzanita from there. Cottonwood usually has drinking water year-round, but it didn’t when we hiked, because of COVID-19 concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Manzanita, we found some benches, restrooms, and drinking water. It was an hour past midnight when we got there and my friend started to feel sleepy. Since the next section was the hardest of the whole hike, or so we thought, it seemed like a good idea to take a nap and a snack break before we continued. With just the two of us out there in the dark, I didn’t feel comfortable also sleeping while he was asleep, so I stayed awake, snacking and thinking. Reflection, when not filled with negative and toxic thoughts, can be an effective antidote to boredom. You need no one and nothing else but your own company. I also loaded up on some caffeine to help push through the uphill that was staring at us in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-3-manzanita-to-the-north-rim&quot;&gt;Section 3. Manzanita to the North Rim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six miles were uphill with steep grades, all the way to the North Rim. You gain about 4k-4.5k ft in elevation. For someone who hasn’t done it before, the six miles can feel like sixteen. It just doesn’t end. Time flies, but the trail seems to not care about it. Every mile felt like two and every switchback looked like an unwelcome surprise. Around 4.30 am when we were a few miles away from the top, I looked up and saw the Milky Way. I wished I could stop to take a photo, but I neither had the patience, nor the time and energy for it. Every second was important and so was every step. I had to keep moving. The trail wasn’t going to magically slide beneath my feet. We weren’t even half the way yet. So I quietly soaked myself in the landscape for a few seconds, expressed my gratitude for the good fortune I had to be able to enjoy this, and continued climbing. At 6 am, we made it to the North Rim, exactly twelve hours after where we’d started from, which now seemed like a faraway land. There was nobody there but us. Looking at the vast canyon from that vantage point, I felt like someone who had lost contact with the civilization and was trying to find their way back home. It was cold there so we didn’t stay long. Knowing that it was six miles downhill again was comforting and helped us keep going. The day was getting brighter but the sun was still making its way above the canyons. It felt like the sun and I were fighting the same uphill battle in some ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-4-back-to-manzanita&quot;&gt;Section 4. Back to Manzanita&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from the rim, I took a ten-minute nap somewhere on the trail under the warmth of the sun, which was now up and shining in my face. In a couple of hours, we were back in Manzanita, which was now crowded, full of runners, who were making this hike look easy with their banters, laughs, and light packs. Lack of sleep that I had started increasingly feeling and the pain that started to show itself in various parts of the body made me sulk at the runners. Not that they cared, but I sulked away for my comfort. Some more snacks and water and we took off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-5-back-to-phantom-ranch&quot;&gt;Section 5. Back to Phantom Ranch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were back on the flats again, but after twenty-eight miles of hiking even that felt challenging. The shoulders yelled with each step at the weight I was carrying. The back had similar complaints. I took breaks and dropped my backpack every hour in an attempt to put them at ease. But they’d scream soon as I started. There was a long way to go still, so no amount of self-pity could have helped. One of the things about putting yourself out there in nature is that it doesn’t take long to find out that it’s an unbeatable force and so the only way out is to make peace with your finiteness, and then to ask, with humility, for some mercy, and muster all the courage and will that you have. Unlike with people, when you’re up against nature, anything that happens to you is on you. It has no bias, no motives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the section was a chance to get lemonade. The store at the Phantom Ranch area was now open and serving snacks and cold drinks. The thought of an iced lemonade pushed me in the last few miles. When I had visualized the hike days before the hike, in order to mentally prepare, I had thought about all the things I’d think about during the hike. I also thought about what’d motivate me when things got hard. I didn’t think lemonade would be it. It’s amazing, and naive, how we think we’re in control of our thoughts, but often are nothing more than mere observers of the ones that come to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of us sipped a glass of lemonade and then I took a twenty-minute nap on a nearby bench. It was close to 1.30 PM, I think. After the nap and some futile attempts at motivating each other, we started moving. It was close to 2.30 PM when we started towards the final leg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;section-6-the-final-leg---back-to-the-south-rim&quot;&gt;Section 6. The Final Leg - Back to the South Rim&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was trying to avoid even thinking about this section in the hope that if I never thought about it, it’d magically get better. It’s this denial of reality, or rather, firm belief in the myth that problems go away by not addressing them that turns a seemingly harmless piece of stone into an avalanche over time. We do this all the time – a difficult conversation with a friend or a colleague, or emotional troubles that haven’t been paid attention to – not thinking about problems is one way to avoid them, and so is getting drunk, but the sooner we acknowledge the better. “Slow and steady”, I told myself, “and I’ll make it”. “Slow” it certainly was, not so sure about “steady”. I felt like I didn’t even care much about finishing the hike at that point, that all I wanted to do was drop the pack and be done. The only thought that pushed me was knowing that the more I slowed the worse it got. We were already cutting it pretty close to the 24-hour mark and the last shuttle ran an hour past sunset. Missing that would mean walking one more mile to the car. So one leg in front of the other and I kept moving. At 7.30 pm, 25.5 hours after I had started, I dropped dead back at the trailhead, pale, sunburnt, and with no juice left in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We caught the shuttle back to the car, cooked and ate dinner before heading to the campsite. At the campsite, we crawled straight into our sleeping bags, only to see each other the next morning. Around 9 AM, we packed our stuff, took shower at the Tusayan General Store and started to drive back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reflections-on-the-way-back-home&quot;&gt;Reflections on the way back home&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental preparation is key for such challenges. If someone asked me to walk 47 miles on city streets, I’d gladly reject the offer. I’d say that I’d be physically incapable of doing it, but I’d be lying. The truth is that it’d mentally exhaust the heck out of me, and that lack of intent would make sure that I quit, well before I reach my physical limits. It was the magnificence of the canyon, the respect this hike commanded, and the reputation it had, that helped me view this as a challenge worth pursuing and pushed me enough to finish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound preposterous to say that any athletic undertaking like that is more of a mental effort than a physical one, but it’s not very different from something that we are all too familiar with – cleaning the dishes. Cleaning the dishes is an activity that couples and housemates universally fight over, or argue about. But if you think about it, there’s no great physical labor involved in doing it, and it’s not that hard. If you do it everyday, it’d hardly take 15 minutes for most people. It’s the psychological baggage that comes with it, the societal or cultural values attached to it, that makes us want to avoid doing it, and the consistency required to do it well. The first part prevents you from getting your ass to the kitchen sink, the latter part is what makes it difficult every damn day. You might say then that the friction to doing the dishes is a result of mental hurdles more than physical ones, and so it is with an ultra-hike or an ultra-run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the weeks leading up to the hike, I visualized myself being on my feet in the canyons for 24 hours without sleep and food. Of course, I didn’t know what it’d feel like, because I hadn’t done it before, but it helped me get familiar with the idea of walking for that long. I went over the uphills, the downhills, and the flats of the trail repeatedly while staring at the maps, telling myself that it wasn’t that bad. I educated myself about the hydration and fueling strategies and convinced myself that I’d take them seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of it was as I’d imagined it to be. And the surprises taught me something about the gaps in my imagination. The landscape was more beautiful than the canyons of my thoughts, the downhills were harder on the knees than I thought, and the uphill was more brutal than I prepared mentally for. Shoulders and back hurt more than the legs which came as a total surprise. As far as fueling goes, it turns out that when the body is in pain and discomfort, it rejects food, and so the twelve pounds of the backpack I chugged the whole way, like a mule, was for nothing. I had downloaded audiobooks and motivational podcasts into my phone to listen to, but I learned that no amount of external motivation can make up for the lack of internal drive. It’s only when I talked myself into putting one leg in front of the other did I make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While climbing up the North Rim, less than halfway through the hike, I kept telling myself that I had reached my limit. The line from the sign came roaring back to me.. “Don’t be one of them.. Know your limits”. It was interesting how every step, after a point, felt like the last step I could take, but somehow every step convinced me that I could take one more. The concept of limit seemed plastic. The more I stretched it, the more it kept stretching, without snapping, which tells me that the limits that we think are physical, in most cases, are in the mind. The quote I read somewhere now makes sense, “The mind always gives up before the body”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the hike, when I was telling my friends and family that my legs felt relatively good, and that the back and shoulders were doing much worse, I learned something insightful. My legs were ready for the distance. Had I dropped my pack and went light, with a bottle of water and some snacks, I could have done it much faster and the experience would have been much smoother. Running the trail somehow started to look doable. I told myself that I was going to attempt running it in the following year. I also realized that my legs would have been okay walking a few more miles, which tells me that 65 mi, i.e. 100k is well within reach, of course, with some physical and mental training. That’d be the next formidable challenge worth chasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the activity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/5191472030&quot;&gt;Strava&lt;/a&gt;, for the curious ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/endurance/reflections/outdoors/2021/05/03/grand-canyon-r2r2r.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/endurance/reflections/outdoors/2021/05/03/grand-canyon-r2r2r.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>endurance</category>
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
        <category>outdoors</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Runs in Thoughts in Runs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was young, my mom, my brother and I used to make at least two trips every summer. One was to my maternal grandparents’ place and one to my paternal ones’. The places and the experiences from the two couldn’t have been more different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal grandparents’ home was a relatively comfortable place in an old cotton mill town and had all the comforts and luxuries that we wanted – new clothes that mom would buy for us, theaters to watch the latest movies with our uncles, good restaurants to be treated with the best food in town, and street food to test the limits of our taste buds and young digestive systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paternal grandparents lived in a small village, in a place beside the areca and coconut farms that we owned, with my dad’s younger brother and his wife. My dad had left the village when he was young, against his father’s liking, and had moved to town to make a better living. The oldest son, in Indian society, carries certain status and expectation. The idea of my father, the oldest son of his parents, leaving his village, home, parents and the farm, was not something that my grandfather approved of. They hardly ever spoke eye to eye after that. The admiration and love they had for each other hadn’t gone down, but the damage done to their male egos never completely healed. None of us ever talked about it. We were too young then, and it’s too late now. I can only surmise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a humble living in the village, with no dearth of love and affection, but only of the material things. In summer there were power outages that spanned days, sometimes weeks, at a stretch, and nothing much to do. We had a few cows and calves, and a couple of cats and dogs. Feeding them, cuddling them and walking them around was what we did for entertainment. Over the years it turned into a hobby. It amazes me how repetition of an activity changes our brain. We often end up going from being averse to something, to being comfortable with it, to liking it, and sometimes to a point of no return. Every morning we went to take a dip in a nearby river right in front of the village temple, a short walk from our home. The time we spent in the village has been, in retrospect, more memorable than the city life we lived for the majority of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water in the river was clear, cold, and ankle-deep during the summer; the bed rugged and rocky.  Adults helped us cross the stream when we were little. As we grew older, we became more capable and independent. We had learned the necessary skills to make our way across without tripping or falling in water. Rarely do we now encounter such intimate moments with nature. As we made it past childhood to adulthood, we comfortably crossed not merely the river, but also the thin line between confidence and arrogance. What we once viewed as a force of nature to be admired, and regarded, became dull, inconsequential, and even inconvenient. Thanks to climate change, the force really did decline, with the amount of water now hardly enough to fill an aquarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrogance seems to be an unfortunate truth, not merely of individuals, but of our species as a whole. We think we are the ones in charge, not only of our lives, but of everything around us. We think that we possess the capacity to bend the world to our will, rather than being good citizens of the planet with a fair share of compromises to make and fulfilling our obligations towards it. We forget that while we might have the ability to choose our actions, we’re not in control of the outcomes, that they are up to the forces external to us, and bigger, more powerful than us. We forget that the metaphorical rocks underneath, going back to those streams, could be slippery, and the water turbulent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are all kinds of things that could go wrong in the space that exists between our actions and the their outcomes. If nothing does, well, we do what we do best, pat ourselves on the back and move on with our smugness unshaken, or emboldened. It’s those of us who experience helplessness and vulnerability in the face of a challenge too big to overcome who often possess the humility and grace to accept the truth of our fallibility, limits and weaknesses, and of our place in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, when I had recollections of these old memories from childhood, a weird and amusing thought came to me. I wondered if I was crossing the river while it was flowing, or if the river was flowing while I was crossing. It wasn’t a scientific answer I was looking for, but a philosophical one. A few days after, while I was running, I found myself pondering over a similar thought, in a different setting. I was asking myself if I think while running or run while thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts, like a stream of water, are perennially flowing, and perpetually changing their course. Running, on the other hand, is deliberate and has a concrete start and stop to it. I guess there’s a philosophical argument that can be made that in some sense we’re all running towards something all the time, but that’s not the kind of running I’m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I’d like my thinking also to be deliberate, I find out every time that thoughts can neither be summoned nor be directed at will. Well, I guess that’s not completely true. When we have control over the mind, we can, but when we gain control of the mind is not exactly up to us. It’s dictated by the mind itself. So it’s not as much as taking control, as it is accepting it, when it’s relinquished by our mind. The mind has its hierarchy of needs. When the base ones have been met, it lets you focus on things that are, while important, matter the least, relatively speaking. The less turbulent it is, the better your chances of being able to exercise your will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I start running, for example, the first few thoughts are about how my body is feeling. I can’t help it. They just occur to me. This is what I call the “safety system” talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is my body hurting? Legs, back, neck, feet?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Is this a safe area? Do I have enough control of the environment?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re followed by thoughts about the logistics of the run. This is the “optimization system” doing its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I going too fast, or slow?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How long do I want to run?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Is my form proper?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Am I landing on my forefeet?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How long can I comfortably run, considering how much I ran yesterday?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How much do I plan to run the rest of the week?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What do I listen to?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do I have my tracker on?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running pace dictates how clearly I can think. Run too fast and the “safety system” kicks in, taking control back. Run too slow and the “optimization system” takes charge. The pace has to be in a sweet spot where both the systems are content and quiet. That pace is different for everybody, and it changes over time and with context. I think that’s true not merely with running, but with life. We all have a pace we’re comfortable with and goals we aspire to, but knowing what they are takes time and deliberate effort. When I’m training for a race, I want to be more mindful about the pace. When I’m running to get over a hard, or bad, day, I don’t care as much, when I’m running to think, I might run slower than usual. My pace is probably faster than some, and certainly slower than a lot of other people, but as long as I’m enjoying the run and it’s serving the purpose I run for, it doesn’t matter much. When you find the pace you’re comfortable with, you hit a rhythm, at which point putting one leg in front of the other becomes as mechanical as pedaling a bike. Depending on how you’re feeling and the amount of gas left in you, that repetition can go on for as long as you want. That’s when the mind decides that it’s okay for you to take over and focus on what you want to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about thinking, “shower thoughts” come to mind. People often stumble upon good ideas in a shower. I do, too. But I feel like the five or ten minutes it takes me to finish one is not long enough to think through those ideas. It doesn’t provide me the continuity required to go deep into anything, unless, of course, I stay there long enough to let the hot water wash away not merely the dirt, but peel my skin along with it. Shower thoughts make for a good tweet. They can be smart, creative, funny, or even profound. Like people scrolling endlessly on the Internet glancing at posts and moving on, so do you — you mentally “like” the idea, feel good about yourself and move on to the next thought. There’s no dearth of such shower thoughts to scroll through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the few times in the day I get uninterrupted alone time long enough to think through things is while running. It also provides me with a conducive environment to focus so I can dig into the thoughts, peel the layers, connect different ideas and organize them. It gives me the resources to play with the Lego blocks that are thoughts and build a concrete, stable structure out of them. It helps me better understand myself better and the world around me. Thoughts on a run make for good long-form writing, and I say good, not in a pompous way, but rather with a humble realization that the amount of attention involved stands to benefit you in more than one way. At worst, you’ll have spent time trying to understand the nuances of things, and you’ll have emerged having learned something. At best, you’ll have created something that others will find value in and will pay for with their time and attention, which is as valuable a currency as one can hope for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned from running that it matters more that you run, than where and when you do. So while this might seem like one big, confused rambling, the inquiry has proved useful to me. I now know more about the thoughts I have while running and I know that as long as I’m exercising my mental and physical muscles, I’m making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/running/musings/2021/04/02/runs-in-thoughts-in-runs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/running/musings/2021/04/02/runs-in-thoughts-in-runs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>running</category>
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Old Memory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day, I remember, as I was riding in the back of my colleague’s motorbike, in some of the fancy neighborhoods of Bangalore. I don’t even remember his full name. We called him &lt;em&gt;Khan Sir&lt;/em&gt;. You didn’t have to have knighthood to be addressed as &lt;em&gt;Sir&lt;/em&gt; in India. It was merely a sign of respect, a polite acknowledgement of your age, knowledge or experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was about a week after our CEO told us that we were shutting down due to lack of sufficient funding. This was a perfect opportunity for the entrepreneurial-minded, and Khan Sir was one. He had an idea that he wanted to work on, to try and make a product, and eventually a company, out of it. He had always wanted to give it a shot, but the resistance that comes from comfort and a fat paycheck can be hard to battle. This was the window and the push he was secretly wishing for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wanted a dummy to turn his idea into a working prototype. I was willing to help, a young and naively energetic and optimistic engineer, trying to grab every opportunity that presented itself. I was waiting to fly to the US for my Master’s degree in a few months, so I had nothing to lose if this little tinkering didn’t work, and something to gain if it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After building an MVP, we traveled on his motorbike to pitch the idea to potential investors. That’s when I first visited some of the rich homes of the Silicon Valley of India. These were the people that made it all happen. They listened to people all day long, sifted through the pile of ideas and the list of people with ideas, and funded the ones that they thought had the potential to make it big. We sure thought we were one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those brief rounds with Khan Sir taught me more about him, his motivations and aspirations than a year working with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the stops we made, we parked the bike right next to a dog that was sleeping on the street. Our arrival was an unwelcome change in his world. How do I know? His face told us that. Turns out animals are good at communicating non-verbal clues. At least that was my interpretation of it. I would have been pissed if somebody woke me up from my mid-day nap. I guess that tells more about me than what the dog was &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I suppose he didn’t know, or care, that it was mid-day, or even mid-week. It’s not like he had some place he’d rather be, or something he’d rather be doing. He was right where he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to be, precisely when he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to be, doing exactly what he &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to do. He probably also didn’t have any cultural notions about what he ought to do with his life. That seems like something only animals as smart as us could come up with, and then brood over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts about meaning and purpose, of why we are here, consumes most of us at various points in our life. Sometimes so much that it pushes us over the edge of uncertainty and leaves us rolling down helplessly and endlessly because the answers don’t come easy. It dictates, consciously or not, things we do with our time, and hence with our lives. Different cultures and societies, as do different individuals, have different ideas about them. For some, it’s about pleasing God, or working towards a divine reward. For others, it’s about living a good life, whatever that means, a life of virtues and principles, perhaps. For some, it’s the pursuit of knowledge, and for others, it’s about finding their true potential, exploring the limits of their body and mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the dog. There was something very peaceful about the way he was sleeping amidst all the noise around him. For a moment, I felt like trading lives with him. As I was thinking it, Khan sir interrupted my chain of thought and said something along the same lines. He said he’d have preferred to be born as a dog, so that he didn’t have to worry about building a company, or about finding meaning in life. He felt like trading lives with the dog too! The zen-like state that the dog was projecting, of being able to tune out the external noises and the internal voices and being completely immersed in what he enjoyed was enviable. It’s what we all strive to achieve, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted the dog’s life because I was lazy. I’d rather be sleeping than working. But for him, it was deeper than that. He was, I now realize, dealing with the dichotomy of pain and pleasure that comes from being driven. Internal drive, just like external ones, can be ruthless at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had a wife and a kid. His wife was pregnant at the time with the second one and had gone to her mother’s place for six months. So he had given himself six months to work on his idea. He had saved enough to make it work, without work. It’s kind of a short deadline though, and a hard one, knowing that you got half a year to turn the abstract in your mind into something concrete in the real world, and knowing that this was one of those rare moments when things fall into place to open a narrow window of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His passion to make an impact in the world was pushing him towards something that was hard and uncomfortable yet rewarding at the same time. He felt the agony of spending all that time away from his kid and his then-pregnant wife, of life slipping away from his hands without him being present with his loved ones, but also experienced the joy that comes from attending to the calling from within. He’d have preferred an easier life if he could, but his drive left him no choice. I learned recently that that idea or state is explained through the concept of positive liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I couldn’t empathize with him. I wasn’t passionate about anything, and I didn’t have responsibilities of anyone but my own. Time, as far as I was concerned, was a perennial resource. I had the majority of my life ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was in the year 2013, which seems like a long time ago now. The memory of this whole episode kept coming back to me at various times, in different situations, years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, in 2016, when I started to become interested in outdoor activities and got into running, hiking, and biking, I remember how I couldn’t get myself to do anything during the weekends but that. The rush and excitement was irresistible. Friday evening, I hit the road, only to be back home on Sunday. Every weekend a new destination, with new people. Even my day job took a backseat for a while. I focused less on my career and more on such experiences. With this new found freedom, I thought, and read, a lot about balance and free will but at the same time felt completely helpless in the grips of the inner force that was controlling me. It occurred to me how he, or most entrepreneurs, must feel like when they invest all their precious resources – time, money, and energy – into building something, knowing well that the chances of it going anywhere good are rather slim. It’s hard to tell if it’s what you are choosing to do, or if it’s the inner voice making you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, in 2021, while sitting on a couch dragging my fingers against the iPad screen, looking for e-books in my library app, I stumbled upon a book called &lt;em&gt;“How to Teach Philosophy to Your Dog - Exploring the Big Questions in Life”&lt;/em&gt;, by Anthony McGowan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title piqued my interest for two reasons: first, because of my interest in books that break down complex subjects into simple language, and second, because I was curious about how ideas from a subject, as complex and as abstract as Philosophy, could possibly be transported out of the realm of human understanding and extended to a dog’s world. The title also brought back that old memory and for a moment, my mind drifted away…wondering about that dog…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was he still alive? What would he be doing with his life now, if he were?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over all these years, would he have grown in some way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did old age teach him lessons he would tell his younger self? All those days spent sleeping, could they have been spent any better, in a more productive way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and wondering about freedom…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was the dog freer than us, in a way, without being constantly crippled by the worries in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is free will and freedom reflected in what we do, or what we &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is the latter, are we &lt;em&gt;choosing&lt;/em&gt; to do the things we do in our life, or are we merely telling ourselves that to be able to sleep at night? If we’re acting purely and solely based on our impulses, are we even exercising our freedom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07VS3WFK2/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;How to Teach Philosophy to Your Dog: Exploring the Big Questions in Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/liberty-positive-negative/&quot;&gt;Positive and Negative Liberty: Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 23:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reflections/2021/02/28/an-old-memory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reflections/2021/02/28/an-old-memory.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>About Simple and Obvious Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One afternoon at work I had a meeting to release the last piece of a project that was meant to change the way our clients interacted with the backend systems. It was a fairly simple routing change at the load balancer and was expected to be done in a few minutes. Not all people invited were strictly required in the meeting, so while a few joined, others kept an eye on their respective systems for any potential misbehaviours and followed a Slack channel for constant updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, talking with a few people on the video call, and texting a couple more on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five minutes into the meeting, we did the change and shifted our attention to the monitoring systems to see early signs of success, or to minimize damage in the remote possibility of a failure. Twenty minutes later, we still didn’t see any activity that we’d expected or hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the change was such that it was expected to take a short period to propagate but we didn’t know, or could tell, how long exactly. So we didn’t sweat. We had theories about why it might be taking longer than usual. About thirty minutes later, we decided to involve somebody from the iOS team to simulate tests from the clients’ perspective to get some validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They took their sweet time to prepare their devices and simulators for the test. After about fifteen minutes, we finally tested it and saw some errors. When we dug into it, we learned that our customers had been seeing those errors in Production all this time since I made the change about fifty minutes ago! What was weird was that no whistles and bells went off, no pages were triggered, so, for a moment, we doubted if the customers did, in fact, have any negative impact. In any case, we reverted the change, just to be safe. The errors, as you’d guess, went away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first learned about the impact of the incident, I felt embarrassed and a little nervous. For how business-critical this was, fifty minutes was enternity! We should have known long before that. But the guilt and embarrasment was not because it could have been avoided — that realization only came later — but because I instantly started questioning my abilities. I was trusted with it, and I was incapable of executing it. It was my lack of knowledge and technical skill, I thought, that was the problem, and my self-doubt started to eat me up. To calm down the inner voice, I even went into denial and started blaming other people for it, at least in my mind, if not in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it was all dealt with, my manager called me on my phone to have a chat. He was kind and responsible enough to reflect on it and think of ways he could have helped me. But there was one thing he mentioned which guided my thinking in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asked me what my plan was before I got into the meeting. How dare he ask me what the plan was, I thought. Was he hinting that I didn’t or doubting if I had a plan at all? I obviously had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into the meeting assuming that I knew all that had to be done, and I didn’t anticipate anything going wrong. Saying that I didn’t anticipate is an understatement. I was so confident that nothing would go wrong that I didn’t consider any options for when it did go wrong. It wasn’t a gap in my knowledge that was the problem, but lack of thought and foresight, about the potential consequences and impact of the change on the system as a whole, both good and bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many pieces to this change and even though each one of those was fairly simple, they had to be executed in a specific order, and more importantly every one of those was cruicial to the success. And because of their fragmented nature, it was really easy to miss a couple of steps and roll down the metaphorical stairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atul Gawande, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right/dp/0312430000&quot;&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right&lt;/a&gt;, mentions an essay from the 1970s by philosophers Samuel Gorovitz and Alasdair MacIntyre, which talks about human fallibility. One reason they talk about for why things go wrong is “necessary fallibility”, which is when they’re beyond our capacity to control. These, by definition, can’t be prevented from happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he identifies two other reasons — &lt;em&gt;ignorance&lt;/em&gt;, the gaps in our knowledge, and &lt;em&gt;ineptitude&lt;/em&gt;, our failure to apply the knowledge correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignorance, if we’re willing to learn, can be reduced over time; the more time we put into something, the more we learn about it, the more knowledge we gain. But competence is something that doesn’t build over time. Getting rid of ineptitude, in other words, building competence, requires discipline, patience, and deliberate practice. In fact, there’s a case to be made that the more knowledge we possess, the more likely it is to blind ourselves to a holistic, systems thinking approach unless we’re constantly reevaluating ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having the necessary knowledge to execute the task at hand, I had failed to come up with a plan, a checklist of things that I should have had in place before I jumped on it. But my mistake had a meta nature to it. I knew the importance of checklists, but had failed to put that knowledge too, which made me aware of the difference between theory and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the incident, I finally started taking the idea of checklists, the habit of note-taking, seriously. I especially note things that seem simple and obvious, because those are the ones that are likely to be missed, by everybody. If there’s one thing I’ve learned from my experience is that things that seem simple and obvious, are not necessarily easy and not so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Avoidable failures are common and persistent, not to mention demoralizing and frustrating, across many fields -- from medicine to finance, business to government. And the reason is increasingly evident: the volume and complexity of what we know has exceeded our individual ability to deliver its benefits correctly, safely, or reliably. Knowledge has both saved us and burdened us.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right/dp/0312430000&quot;&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2020/06/27/simple-and-obvious.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2020/06/27/simple-and-obvious.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Chat With the Different Selfs</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
We all have various sides of our self, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about how the pandemic has affected me, I can’t think of one absolute way it has. The experience hasn’t been binary, one that can be categorized into good or bad. We all have various sides of our &lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;, and each of them has their own thoughts and stories about experiences. And though there are hundreds of dimensions to it, there are some we identify ourselves with more than others, some that feel more us to us than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to think about what those are for me, bring them to light, and get them to talk. Most of them have adapted quite well to the changes necessitated by the constraints of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-different-selfs&quot;&gt;The different selfs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we spend a better part of our lives doing our day job, it naturally defines us in a significant way, if not completely. I work as a software engineer, and it’s one of my important identities, it’s also the one that’s most visible or known to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the integral parts of my job, an activity that is also close to my heart, is to always keep learning. That’s another thing I identify myself with - as someone eager to learn and open to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental, and in some ways more important, part of my identity is one that’s obsessed with practising a healthy lifestyle. I say important because I believe it nourishes the other selfs, and fundamental because it’s less fluid in nature than the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other important dimension is the part of me that cares deeply about animals. I say &lt;em&gt;cares&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt;, because that’s an important distinction, and even though I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; some animals, I want to be mindful about the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one other aspect of me has stood the test of time. I don’t have much control over it, and I’ve had a love-hate relationship with it, more hate than love - my introverted nature. More hate than love because I’ve only recently started to accept, and nurture it, rather than treating it like a problem that needed fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next one is a close kin of the self that wants to lead a healthy life, but is more opinionated on how to go about it. It believes in spending time in nature, and doing physically challenging things to keep the body and the mind in good shape. The curious and learning part of me constantly feeds this self, with new ideas, challenges to tackle and goals to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one I can think of is the most volatile of them all, and has only come to consciousness very recently. It swims up to the surface and goes back to hiding depending on the things that’s happening around me - the one that thinks of itself as an immigrant in a foreign country, a guest in someone else’s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I try to prod each one of them to express their thoughts about how they feel being sheltered in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-a-software-engineer&quot;&gt;As a software engineer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s fairly easy to work remotely and still be productive. While I miss the walks and talks around the office with my peers to get coffee during the day, I’ve made up for it by experimenting with different kinds of plant-based milk coffees at home. After several weeks of trial-and-error, it’s getting close to my liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate that wifi at home is not as good and causes, part frustrating, part funny, technical issues while talking to my colleagues on video calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also miss the desk setup and multiple monitors I used to have in the office, but for now, I’m managing with an REI camp chair, a laptop and a monitor. It’s easy to get lost in work and forget how or where I’m sitting at home. Stiffness from bad body postures used to be a problem in the first weeks, but I’ve gotten more mindful about that over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/engineer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to wait for meeting rooms to free up to chat with people - they’re just a few clicks and a video call away. I think it’s more productive and collaborative than an open-office setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that I don’t have to rush to catch the train and sit through a long commute to get to work in the morning, and that I can start working early in the day when my mind is at its best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first few weeks, I worked more than usual, and so did my peers. But I’ve gotten better at drawing boundaries between work and personal life, even without a physical one separating the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing I don’t miss is the incessant chatter in the office, where unnecessary small talk is confused with collaboration and coding is confused with mindless typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the things I don’t miss from going to work and the things I love about working from home, I’d do more remote work going forward for sure, and hope companies embrace it more too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-avid-reader&quot;&gt;As an avid reader,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that the two or more hours I used to spend riding in train to go to work, I now spend riding in train of thoughts, one that takes me to farther and better places. Reading not only helps me unplug from the stress and concerns of work, but the comfort and peace of doing it from home improves my mood. The absence of distractions of a typical workday has helped me do more of a fewer things rather than juggle a little bit of everything. Long stretches of undistracted time allows me to focus on reading books, long-form articles and write more, rather than filling the tiny slices of time over the day with news and junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absence or lack of something usually makes you realize its importance, but it’s interesting in a way that having more, and not less, time in hand has made me realize how much of it was being taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/reading.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also starting to see the benefits of consistency and discipline, of cultivating enough patience to do something everyday despite the initial aversion and resistance, and how it can make a big difference relatively quickly. Though I have been trying to get into the habit of writing for over a year, I’ve only been this consistent and serious about it since I started working from home. The world had to hit brakes on its operations and get rid of distractions for me to start writing. It’s like the Universe really wanted to teach me good habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-outdoor-enthusiast&quot;&gt;As an outdoor enthusiast,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really worried about not being able to travel. I had a few races that I had signed up for and a few trips I had planned for this year. But sitting at home, not having hiked or biked in a couple of months now has taught me that I don’t need to go to new places to freshen up my mind, or to enjoy outdoors every time I head out. That I can just step out of the door and start running until I get tired and run back. That it can be that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started running a couple of years ago for the fun of it, and maybe a little to lose weight too, but over time, I started getting obsessed over quantifying the benefits of every activity - the calories burnt, pounds lost, and speed etc,. I’m now back to those simple days. Not every run now goes in Strava, not every race has to end up in PRs, not every walk now is a hike and not every bike ride is captured in photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/outdoor.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solace I used to find in the outdoors, I’ve found it in reading and writing too. Although there is something magical about being out in nature, I realize that one of the reasons it felt so good was the time it gave me to pause, and reflect on things. Turns out books do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-introvert&quot;&gt;As an introvert,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m in love with the silence. It not only helps me think clearly, and be more productive at work, it also puts me in a much better mood overall. Even after working long hours, I find that I have the time and energy to go on walks with my wife, cook, go for a run, read, write and talk to friends and family on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/introvert.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the idea of minimizing sounds that fall in my ears, the idea of letting them in willingly rather than being bombarded with unnecessary and unsolicited noises all day long and being forcefully made a passive member in every conversation around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-immigrant&quot;&gt;As an immigrant&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from India, I see the contrast in how people from the two countries are reacting to the pandemic, both common people and those in power. Being from the majority group in India, and a part of one of the minority groups(immigrants) here in the US, it gives some perspectives on how stereotypes and misinformation against minorities are used for political and capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’m concerned about the well-being of older members of my family back home and wish I were there, a part of me feels relieved that I’m not with them to inadvertently infect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/immigrant.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see through the lies and the facade of developed societies and feel hopeful and optimistic, to see the potential of the developing nations and their simple, yet effective ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the things that have worked for countries and things that haven’t, I realize that more technology is not necessarily the right solution to all problems. Common sense and empirical evidence are perfectly fine at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;as-an-animal-rights-believer&quot;&gt;As an animal rights believer,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that non-humans have started to come out of hiding and are doing so without the fear of us harming, or killing them, that at least for a little while they regain their rights over the resources of this planet, and not everything they consume are left-overs from humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://outofdesk.github.io/static/img/pandemic/animals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m terribly sad and shocked by the fate of hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of animals in factory farms that were killed because humans couldn’t afford to raise and kill them to eat. I can’t decide which is worse, simply killing them, or killing to eat them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that meat substitutes are seeing tremendous growth and hope that the trend continues long after our lives get back to &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt;. Although it’s a result of shortage of meat in markets right now, I hope that reduced meat and dairy consumption becomes the new normal, and people see it for what it actually is, and the problems it puts us into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slow-life-vs-fast-life&quot;&gt;Slow life vs fast life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say the world has slowed down during the pandemic, but what does it mean to be slow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we truly slowed now, or were we unnecessarily fast before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was the rush anyway, and where were we all headed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were we navigating towards a perceived sense of growth and success, or were we merely racing towards a mountain of problems created by our own greed and speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the rush was in fact necessary, why does slow feel better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the age of mind and innovation, than of body and physical labor, then why were cruising in autopilot, without stopping to think about the destination?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that the fast life we chose in pursuit of something good only made us more miserable and unhealthy, and this life of nothingness is making us happier, and healthier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ironic that we’re regaining the connections we had lost, by distancing ourselves? That we had to be physically social-distanced to close the mental and emotional gap between each other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas and learnings from a lot of reading and collaboration between multiple dimensions of my self has gone into producing this. Of all the news and information that’s out there about the pandemic, a majority of them either portray humans as the victims, not the villains, or blame a specific section of people for all the problems. With such lopsided, and biased opinions floating around, this one below stands out with a different perspective on things and makes for a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I’ve come to shut down the machine whose emergency brake you couldn’t find
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lundi.am/What-the-virus-said&quot;&gt;What the virus said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reflections/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reflections/2020/05/14/pandemic.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fine Walls</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been more than a month since my wife and I started working from home and about a month since our county placed the shelter-in-place in effect. Our outdoor trips are limited to walk in the evenings, and grocery shopping once a week. The rules and recommendations around the importance and usefulness of everybody wearing a mask are shifting by the day, from being useless one day to being essential the next. That, mixed with the concern of shortage of masks for healthcare workers has caused a surge in videos teaching people how to make DIY masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we went grocery shopping today, the best we could do was use scarves as masks. I realized that there’s something about hiding my face in public that made me feel uncomfortable. Not that it’s a bad idea in these times, but it still feels weird nonetheless, especially the first few times. Maybe it’s a cultural thing or availability bias that has rooted this idea in our minds that bad guys do that - people looting a bank cover their faces, terrorists cover their faces. Sure, doctors and nurses wear masks too, but the human brain doesn’t surface such images when we think about people hiding behind masks. And since face is such a crucial part of our identity, hiding it equates to hiding one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wore the scarf around my face, I also thought about how anti-social it makes us seem. Even in a country like the US, where people try to and encourage minding their business and where people try their best to avoid making accidental eye contact with strangers, wearing a mask seems especially anti-social in some way. It puts a physical boundary between two identities and hence makes the distance between us more real, one that already currently exists but is otherwise invisible. With a mask, you now don’t need to fear awkward eye contact with strangers or running into someone you know but don’t want to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t be surprised if a majority of people here will continue to wear masks after this, not for the fear of infection, but for the liberty to be themselves in public. It’s ironic then that wearing a mask will give us the liberty to throw away the mask of social identity. It looks like a way to disable one of the primary ways we communicate with each other, a way to bring anonymity offered by the Internet out into the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar boundary was drawn not too long ago, to block one of our other primary channels of communication. When I started my first job out of school a few years ago in India, every employee had their cubicle to work. It indicated a piece of space in a huge commercial floor plan which you could call your private little corner. When I got back into the workforce two years later, after attending graduate school, those boundaries were gone, or so I thought. While the idea of open office floor plans was to encourage people to be more social, I learned about the existence of a relatively new, unacknowledged, or rather differently advertised boundary, which wasn’t as far as the walls of cubicles but much closer to us - the headphones. Just like the walls of our homes which signal the borders separating our family from the outside world, headphones draw a boundary between the sounds and voices we &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to let in and everything else. With the introduction of designer and handy AirPods, that boundary has become more commonplace and prevalent and has jumped out of the confinement of the walls of office space. It’s now everywhere – on the trains, on a run, even while having lunch. I can’t help but think and feel bad about the fact that there’s tons of money to be made in the future from the fear we’re now living in and that those solutions will make us, incrementally and permanently, more distant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;@out.of.desk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/musings/2020/04/07/fine-walls.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reading Time</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
But I soon came to feel that teaching these sensitive young souls Latin and mathematics was cheating them of something far more essential — what they needed wasn’t dry information but hope, the kind that comes from being transported into a dream-world of possibility.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Helen Fagin, in The Velocity of Being: Letters to a Young Reader&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a chilly weekend morning. I’m standing on a beach along with tens of other people, all rubbing their hands in a futile attempt to keep themselves warm. The water looks freezing and turbulent as if to throw us back on land if we were to venture out to take a dip. We’re all waiting for the organizers to blow a whistle to start the first leg of the triathlon. The moment it goes off, everybody starts jumping into the ocean like a herd of lemmings out to commit suicide(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalplanet.com/wild-animals/do-lemmings-commit-suicide/&quot;&gt;it’s a myth, they don’t do it&lt;/a&gt;). Although the beach is huge, everybody is cramming into a narrow section where the tides are low. An accidental punch here, a kick there, and the unforgiving water. Bruised and exhausted, I reach the other end to see my bike ready to go. I take off my swim clothes, put on my biking outfit and I’m ready to go. The first half of the biking route is uphill, and that’s where I plan to get ahead of everybody. My quads look like wooden logs that can hardly be contained in the tight shorts. I pedal as fast as I can on the uphill to pass people who beat me in water. At the top, I bring my back closer to the bike frame and take off like a missile launch. Even with the sunglasses, tears from my eyes due to the headwinds fly backward as if they’re going to pierce through the rider behind. At the finish line, I apply the brakes, jump off the bike and let it ride further, and crash on its own, like a bird with its head chopped off. I change to running shorts and gradually up my speed in the last and final activity, the one that seems most familiar and natural to me. I’ve lost track of how many are ahead of me, but halfway into the run, somebody tells me that I have a shot at winning. Tears out again but of joy this time. In the line of sight of the finish line, I almost sprint like my legs are green. I win the event and I see my parents at the finish line clapping and cheering. I see the pride in their eyes, which makes me want to cry more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So vivid is the recollection of the triathlon that never happened. That’s right. I can’t swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.richroll.com/finding-ultra/&quot;&gt;Finding Ultra&lt;/a&gt;, as I read the account of the author’s athletic feats in Hawaii, I pause for a few minutes and get lost in this imaginary race that I’m winning. I probably will never win a triathlon. But that imaginary race was still as real and as powerful a motivator. Three years later, that and many such thoughts have fueled real and positive changes in me. The pride I saw in my parents’ eyes, the joy I felt, although mental images are enough of a force to push me towards the interests and goals I want to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always felt at peace reading a book in a quiet place. I feel invigorated by the journey it takes me onto places that are an amalgamation of physical reality and pure imagination. It’s hugely inspiring and empowering to escape from the conditioning of the real world and into the world of infinite potential and possibilities, to ask yourself the big questions and look for answers within and understand the world a little better. With minimal external influences, you’re on a free ride. Making wrong moves there doesn’t come with the judgments and repercussions of the real world. Instead, they come with a deeper understanding of the consequences of your choices and help you navigate life better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become much harder these days to get the space for yourself, harder than it needs to be. The eight or so hours that you spend at work are flooded with often unnecessary meetings, direct or indirect conversations, and breaks. You go home, spend some time with your partner, do the chores and eke out time to read, write, and workout. Not only do you have to carve time out for deep work, but you also have to make an extra effort to quell the mental chatter caused by entropy throughout the day. With the open floor plans in offices now, the conversations that you become a part of just by being there feel like passive smoking to me. You end up bearing the brunt of something that you didn’t choose to be a part of. It’s a vicious cycle; the more you get used to the distractions, the more uncomfortable you become with quietness and being in your own company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve come to realize, from talking to people and reading books, that I’m more sensitive to sounds around me than most people. It could mean that I get distracted and flustered more too. Although I’ve gotten comfortable plugging headphones while I work, I still prefer quietness to something buzzing in my ears. While it’s an ongoing battle to make space and time for things that you value, it’s a great tool for the unaware. What you fight for gives you a hint at what’s important to you. That clarity gives you the courage to let go of the clutter - both physical and mental, literal and metaphorical. The fight for time is then a fight for values, self-awareness, growth, a fight to discover, shape, and refine yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommended-reading&quot;&gt;Recommended Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2018/12/18/a-velocity-of-being-helen-fagin/&quot;&gt;A 100-Year-Old Holocaust Survivor on How Books Save Lives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;Life is Short&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/reading/2019/11/03/time-to-read.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Ultra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this a few days past my first ultra-marathon. Running, which started as a way to clear my head and lose some weight along the way, has become a much more important part of my life. My relationship to, and the journey of, running is comparable to a relationship between two people. Some things begin to attract you toward them, but after a few rendezvouses, you learn that there’s more to them than meets the eye. While the early fascinations are all real and useful, you realize that they pale compared to the newfound meaning. Not all interactions with people take that course, of course, but when that happens is when you begin to feel the potential of its transformation from scribbles on a blank canvas to a rich, colorful painting. I’ve come to love not merely the looks of running, but the nature of it, the depth of it, the power and the nuances of it. My younger self who started to run a few years ago didn’t have the slightest clue about where it would lead him! Looking back, he looks naive, in a good way, because that naivete and uncertainty are what have made this journey full of pleasant surprises. Setting incremental goals has caused big positive changes over time and in unexpected ways. The thought of running an ultra-marathon was no different; it took shape only a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-big-bike-ride&quot;&gt;The Big Bike Ride&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I had signed up for a long bike ride that was in July. It was an annual race in Colorado, the land of the fourteeners, as they call them, the mountain peaks that stand above 14000 ft from sea level. Much like everybody else who was at the starting line, the competitive nature of the race was one, but not the only, reason that brought me there. People had different motivations, diverse stories, and distinct goals, and expectations from it. I had no intention of trying to be the fastest. Neither had I trained for it nor was I capable of it. It was the longest ride I had ever done in one day and the route wasn’t flat. My goal was to be able to finish it in the allowed time and have fun while doing it. It took us over three mountain passes and the event was aptly called the “Triple Bypass”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a few years since I became an outdoorsman. Having come from a collectivistic society, I’m new to the notion of pursuing one’s interests. Although I’ve embraced it for a while now, it still seems foreign. There’s a part of me that still thinks about whether people will approve of my decisions and how they might affect others. The constant tug-of-war, hitherto undisputed, has now come to a point where my individualistic needs have learned how not to lose every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joy of being in Nature, and of doing things that push your perceived limits is what draws me to seek outdoor challenges. It also brings about a few, seemingly contrasting, virtues — it humbles you and at the same time instills confidence and courage in you. Humility comes from knowing the struggle of pursuing hard things. Confidence and courage come from the knowledge that you can endure it and emerge a little bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-home&quot;&gt;Back Home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I came back home from the race, I got busy with the mundanity of each day. A feeling of emptiness started to creep up a few days later. It was a feeling that seemed vaguely familiar. It was the hole left behind every time I lost something of value. I had felt it before when I lost people who were close. But this time it wasn’t a person that I had lost but a feeling, a sense of progress and growth. In the past few months, the training I did for the race had provided me with the nourishment that I needed, both physical and mental. Now, I was riding the wave of past accomplishment. I hadn’t realized that it had carried me to the beach and left me stranded. Anything that’s worth having in life requires long-term commitment and effort, not merely to gain it but to keep it as well – trust, loyalty, meaning, joy, health. They are the lanes we choose to ride in, not the destinations we choose to get to. I had to get back to the journey, rather than relishing at the stop I had made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know until recently that there’s a word that nicely describes what I was feeling – ennui – the kind of boredom that results from the jadedness of living a life of too much ease. From talking to my friends about it, I’ve come to believe that it’s more common than I had realized. The prevalence of it speaks to the comforts and luxuries in life that we have come to afford as a society. Unlike previous generations, there’s not much in our existence that requires the activation of the wonderful powers that evolution has built into us. We can get through life not having to get off the couch, not feeling warm or cold, not feeling hungry, not feeling bored, not having to interact with another person. I had read somewhere somebody describing it as being in a state of “perpetual homeostasis”. I can’t think of a way to capture it better. Although we think of ourselves as an evolutionary success story, our evolution itself hasn’t caught up to the advances we have made. Our bodies ache to be moved, our brains ache to be stimulated. I sometimes think of us as Hulk whose only workout is carrying a briefcase to the office. Seems like we are all craving for more than that. Whether or not we are aware of that craving is a different matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What Next&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few more weeks passed by as I pushed these thoughts into the background and went about my life. The thought brewed in the subconscious and floated back to the surface a few weeks later, in September. I was turning 30 in October, so running at least 30 miles seemed like an ambitious and fun challenge, something worth working towards. The shortest official distance that matches the criterion is 50k, which is about 32 miles. It also happens to be an ultra-marathon distance. And so the training began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past the Labor Day weekend, so I had already lost the first week of September and since I wanted to do the race in the same month as my birthday, I had about 6-7 weeks to train. It seemed like a short time to go from 0 miles of running the whole year to 50k in a matter of a couple of weeks, but I had built the strength and endurance from the training on the bike. I had to start training for the run as soon as possible. I started the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is what the training looked like in numbers, thanks to Strava.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re into long-distance running, you can tell that they look like casual, weekday runs, nothing like training for an ultra at all, something somebody would do to shake their legs. It’s true. Having made plans for the weekends ahead with my family and friends, weekdays were all I could get. I tried to squeeze at least two runs per week during lunch time, with each run somewhere between 5-8 miles. The longest run was about 10.5 mi and that was three weeks before the race. Sometimes due to lack of time, and other times because of my laziness, I didn’t go longer than that. The runs were on flat roads too, so I wasn’t getting any elevation training either. I had to first build up to the distance, before I could climb up. The race had about 5k ft of elevaton gain and loss. The thought of that, in addition to the pounding of legs for that long, scared me. The last two weeks I ventured out to the hilly streets of San Francisco near my office and did some circuit runs to get my body used to climbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---september&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - September&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-september.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar September&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-calendar---october&quot;&gt;Training Calendar - October&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-calendar-october.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Calendar - October&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-log&quot;&gt;Run Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Log&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-distance&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-time&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-runsin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Training Runs(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/training-runs-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Training Runs(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-distance&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Distance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-distance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Distance)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-time&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Time)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Time)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;race-weekin-elevation-gain&quot;&gt;Race Week(in Elevation Gain)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/race-week-elevation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race Week(in Elevation)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/my-first-ultra/the-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Race&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-reflections&quot;&gt;Notes and Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The race had a no-cup policy, so I carried a Nathan water bottle with me in hand. I think that works better for me than carrying a hydration pack, which rubs my back and gets the shirt all wet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chafing is the worst. Even now, days after the race, my nipples hurt just thinking about it. I think right around mile 13, I took off my shirt and carried it pretty much from there up to a few yards before the finish line. I should take better care of it next time! Vaseline helps but I should look into some strap that hugs it tight and doesn’t cause friction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next time I sign up for something like this, I should do longer runs and on trails. That takes care of the boredom of long runs and also makes for better training&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t get bored in trail runs. I had prepared a playlist of workout music and motivating podcasts to keep me going, especially in the end. But one, I didn’t need it and two, it ruins the fun of the race. When I slowed down in the last third of the race, I enjoyed the company of runners who were with me. Chatting with them, running with them helped me even speed up a little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GU is delicious and works well for my body. It’s really easy to eat on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gear&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newbalance.com/pd/Minimus-Trail-10/190325795818.html?ecid=ps_Google_pla_190325795818_1699205516&amp;amp;crtp=paidsearch&amp;amp;ncr=true&amp;amp;&amp;amp;CATARGETID=172000630002405320&amp;amp;CADevice=c&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAjwxt_tBRAXEiwAENY8hU7bNqAaUvQr4sk556T2MGHF4m5J3F30Jy7qvvDe9b_MznLsEbPS1BoCsSIQAvD_BwE&amp;amp;gclsrc=aw.ds#color=Black_with_Silver&amp;amp;size=8&amp;amp;width=2E&quot;&gt;New Balance Minimus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nathansports.com/collections/hydration/products/speedmax-plus-flask&quot;&gt;Nathan Handheld Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://guenergy.com/products/all-energy-gel&quot;&gt;GU Energy Gels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments about the post, send me a message on any of my social media profiles, or email me at &lt;em&gt;contact.outofdesk [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://outofdesk.github.io/endurance/outdoors/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://outofdesk.github.io/endurance/outdoors/2019/10/28/my-first-ultra.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>endurance</category>
        
        <category>outdoors</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
